<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="principes">
  <title>General Principles</title>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Ergonomics relating to use of an internet
  application</emphasis></para>

  <para>PMB is a web application, a "WebApp". Running on a web server (see the
  <emphasis>PMB Installation Guide</emphasis>, Section 1,
  <emphasis>Installation under Windows,</emphasis> for more information about
  Apache), PMB benefits from the flexibility of internet applications.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Don't use the "previous page" browser
  button.</emphasis></para>

  <para>"Previous page" and "page forward" allow the movement to another page
  on the internet, it is the same in PMB.</para>

  <para><graphic fileref="images/warning.gif" /><emphasis role=""><emphasis
  role="bold">Attention</emphasis></emphasis> Whenever you see on the screen a
  message starting with <emphasis>Update </emphasis>do not click on previous
  page. Whenever you see this message, it is vital to leave the update to
  finish completely. In general, avoid using previous page if you can achieve
  the same results by clicking on one of the links visible on screen.</para>

  <para>Whenever you reload a page which is the result of a form (for example
  adding a new volume), the data is resubmitted to the server.</para>

  <para>Following the same principle as "Previous page", your browser's "Stop"
  button allows the loading of a page to be interrupted.</para>

  <figure>
    <title>Mozilla navigation buttons - Previous page, Page forward, Reload,
    Stop</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/back_mozilla1.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <figure>
    <title>Mozilla navigation buttons - Previous page, Page forward, Reload,
    Stop</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/back_mozilla2.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <figure>
    <title>Internet Explorer navigation buttons - Previous page, Page forward,
    Stop, Reload</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/back_ie.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Attention</emphasis> During important operations
  on the database (additions, deletions), you can not stop the loading of the
  page without interrupting the update in progress, this could risk
  deterioration of the integrity of the database.</para>

  <para>In particular, do not click the "cancel" button when the database is
  being restored, backed-up or optimised.</para>
</chapter>