<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="circ">
  <title>Circulation</title>

  <para>The circulation system of a library means the management of the
  library's holdings in terms of copies of documents and making them available
  to the readers. We often refer to the latter as the charging system.</para>

  <para>The side menu of the circulation tab shows 5 headings : Circulation,
  Display items, Holds, Reminders and Suggestions.</para>

  <para><emphasis>Circulation</emphasis> is for managing readers and
  loans.</para>

  <para><emphasis>Display</emphasis> retrieves information about the library
  collection.</para>

  <para><emphasis>Holds</emphasis> allows you to manage holds placed on works
  available in the library by readers.</para>

  <para><emphasis>Reminders</emphasis> corresponds to sending overdue notices
  to readers for items unreturned by the due date and the recoveries to
  effect. This sub-menu is available only if the financial management of
  readers is enabled, for more details consult the Administrator's guide,
  section Financial management.</para>

  <para><emphasis>Suggestions</emphasis> orders to offer staff and readers the
  possibility to make suggestions for acquisition.</para>

  <sect1 id="circ_circ">
    <title>Circulation</title>

    <sect2 id="circ_pret">
      <title>Loans</title>

      <para>Lending out items to borrowers is very simple : you only have to
      enter the barcode of the reader from his membership card followed by the
      item barcode or accession number. Of course the same transaction can be
      carried out fully using a barcode reader which very conveniently
      replaces the manual entry of the barcode and "enter" on the
      keyboard.</para>

      <para>Obviously there must already be some items and borrowers present
      in the database to allow for issues to be effected.</para>

      <sect3 id="circ_pret_1">
        <title>Borrower Search</title>

        <para>A borrower search works like this: whenever you click on the
        Circulation tab the following screen appears. Enter the full name of
        the borrower or part of it in the text box and press Enter. Of course
        you can also read his barcode ID on his borrower's card with your
        scanner to display his file.</para>

        <para>To display the complete list of borrowers leave the text box
        empty and press Enter. From there you can pick and choose any
        particular user.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Circulation &gt; Loan Items</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/circ_pret.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="circ_pret_2">
        <title>Search results</title>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Example</emphasis>. Let's lend out
        <emphasis>Rwanda : a people with a history</emphasis>, by <emphasis>C.
        M. Overdulve</emphasis>, to our borrower <emphasis>Luke Skywalker
        </emphasis>(with barcode n° 100003).</para>

        <para>His barcode is entered or read by the barcode reader to identify
        the borrower.</para>

        <para>We can also enter all or part of the borrower's name in order to
        select him from a list. For now we will enter the letter "s" for
        Skywalker.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Circulation &gt; Loan (results of a borrower search)</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/circ_pret_2.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Click on borrower Skywalker in the search results list.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="circ_lecteur">
        <title>Borrower's card</title>

        <figure>
          <title>Circulation &gt; Loan (borower card)</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/circ_pret_3.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The barcode of a copy of the Rwanda title is
        33700003286792.</para>

        <para>Just enter this barcode in the "new loan" field to effect the
        loan issue. Press Enter to validate the issue. The loan has been added
        to the list of current loans.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Circulation &gt; Loan, loan added</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/circ_pret_4.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>You can then cancel the loan on the fly by clicking on cancel
        (in this case, the loan is not taken into account for the statistics
        contrary to a validated loan issue immediately followed by a
        return).</para>

        <para>You can also print a loan ticket. It takes the form of a PDF
        file generated by PMB. On Windows the "print loan ticket" button calls
        the Acrobat reader plugin and displays a loan ticket ready to print
        detailing the borrower, the item loaned and the date of return. You
        only have to click on the Acrobat print icon to print the loan
        ticket.</para>

        <para>Starting the Acrobat reader to view the loan ticket can
        sometimes take rather long depending on your computer. In this case
        either be patient or start Acrobat well in advance.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Example of a loan ticket.</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/circ_pret_ticket.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Note.</emphasis> If your item has a
        particular status that does not allow lending, but this rule can be
        overridden, PMB will ask you if you want to force the loan or
        not.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Item is excluded from loan: option to force the loan</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/pret_exclu.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>In our example, the library parameters (name, address, logo) are
        those of the Bueil Library. These parameters can be customized in the
        administration tab. For more information, consult the <emphasis>PMB
        Administrator's Guide</emphasis>, <emphasis>Tools</emphasis>
        section.</para>

        <para>Other available functions from the reader's file:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Effecting an express loan</para>

            <para><figure>
                <title>Express loan button</title>

                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/prolonger_pret_popup.gif" />
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>The express loan enables you to loan items that are
            still in cataloguing. Click on "express loan" to enter the
            information necessary to issue an item that has not yet been
            catalogued.</para>

            <para><figure>
                <title>Express loan</title>

                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/prolonger_pret_popup.gif" />
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>Enter Title and ISBN. Indicate a media type (to be able
            to manage loan periods and quotas consequently).</para>

            <para>Then scan your item barcode, or enter it and
            validate.</para>

            <para>You may afterwards recall the record to complete its
            cataloguing.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Updating borrower data (including membership renewal), see
            Adding a borrower, later in this document.</para>

            <para>To update borrower data, click on the
            <emphasis>Edit</emphasis> button.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Extending an existing loan</para>

            <para>To extend a loan, click on the <emphasis>Due</emphasis>
            button. In the calendar popup, select the new due date. In this
            popup, use the arrows to move forward or backward for months, and
            the double arrows for years.</para>

            <figure>
              <title>Date selection Popup for extending a loan</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/prolonger_pret_popup.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Extending all loans on the fly. Click on the button + to
            select all, then click on the date button "Extend loans of checked
            items until".</para>

            <figure>
              <title>Extending loans on the fly</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/prolonger_pret_popup.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Deleting a borrower: possible only if the borrower has no
            current loans. If there are current loans, the items must be
            returned first.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Printing the loans records: Click on
            <emphasis>Print</emphasis> to print the list of borrowed items and
            current holds, click on <emphasis>Loans list</emphasis> to print
            the current loans for borrower.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Printing the borrower's card</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Adding a new borrower</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <emphasis>add</emphasis> button next to Holds at the
            bottom allows reserve an item.</para>

            <para>After clicking on <emphasis>Add</emphasis>, carry out a
            search. When the item to be placed on hold is found, click on its
            title to insert it into the list of holds.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Borrower's file with Financial management enabled</title>

        <para>Enabling financial management displays the borrower's library
        accounts (membership, loans and fines) underneath his personal
        data.</para>

        <para>If you don't see these three accounts it means financial
        management of readers has not been enabled. For more details, consult
        the Administrator's Guide of PMB, chapter Financial management.</para>

        <para><figure>
            <title>Reader's file showing the membership, loans and fines
            accounts</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/prolonger_pret_popup.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>For more details on the financial management of readers, go
        to the section Loans and financial management further down.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Loans and financial management</title>

      <para>Fro more details on enabling the financial management of readers
      in PMB, refer to the Administrator's Guide, chapter Financial
      management.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title></title>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title></title>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Prêt de document et débit du compte du lecteur du montant d'un
        prêt</title>

        <para></para>

        <para><figure>
            <title>Circulation &gt; Return items</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/circ_retour.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Solde prêt : saisir le paiement du prêt de document</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Retour de document en retard : blocage de prêt et
        amendes</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Solde amendes : gérer le paiement des amendes</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="circ_retour">
      <title>Return items</title>

      <para>Scan the barcode of the item being returned. The borrower card is
      not required.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Circulation &gt; Return items</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/circ_retour.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>A confirmation message is displayed to allow you to check that the
      barcode does correspond to the item being returned.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Circulation &gt; Return items, confirmation of a processed
        return</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/circ_retour2.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>This display gives the borrower name that returned the item.
      Following this is a link which allows access to the relevant borrower
      file, which can be used, for example, to issue new loans.</para>

      <para>Also displayed are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the item type, location, class mark and other copy
          details</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the return is overdue, the number of days late</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The name of the borrower who had the item on loan</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If entered, any message associated with the item</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Any pending holds</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="circ_groups">
      <title>Borrower Groups</title>

      <para>The <emphasis>Borrower groups </emphasis>functionality allows PMB
      to be used by librarians who wish to manage their borrowers by groups:
      classes, familles, etc.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Circulation &gt; Borrower Groups</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/circ_groupes.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="circ_emprcreate">
      <title>New Borrower</title>

      <sect3 id="circ_emprcreate_1">
        <title>Barcode for the new borrower</title>

        <para>A borrower barcode is required whenever you want to create a new
        borrower. I<emphasis>f the pmb.num_carte_auto</emphasis> parameter is
        active (has a value of 1), PMB will suggest a new borrower barcode
        equivalant to the highest barcode in the database +1.</para>

        <para>For more information about the PMB parameters, consult the
        <emphasis>PMB Administrator's Guide</emphasis>, Utils section.</para>

        <para>Once a borrower card number has been defined, click to reach the
        data entry screen for new borrower information.</para>

        <para>Note: Validation (Click on the next button) is automatic with a
        barcode reader.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="circ_emprcreate_2">
        <title>Enter the borrower data</title>

        <para>You can enter the personal information about the borrower on
        this screen.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Circulation &gt; New Borrower</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/circ_nouveau.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>If personnalisable fields were defined in
        <emphasis>Administration &gt; Bororwers &gt; Personalisable
        Parameters</emphasis>, they will be visible at the bottom of the
        borrower file. On the following screen, you can complete the required
        personalisable parameters. To enter a different barcode, replace with
        the barcode of your choice or rescan the new barcode.</para>

        <para>If you enter a barcode which is already allocated, PMB will give
        you an error message.</para>

        <para>To ntoe :</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A surname must always be entered</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A forename must always be entered</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The date of birth is not mandatory if the parameter
            empr.birthdate_optional is selected (has a value of 1). For more
            information, consult the <emphasis>PMB Administrator's
            Guide</emphasis>, <emphasis>Utils</emphasis> chapter,
            <emphasis>Parameters</emphasis> section.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The fields <emphasis>OPAC ID</emphasis> and <emphasis>OPAC
            password</emphasis> define the login ID the borrower can use in
            the OPAC (normally situated at the left of the screen). If these
            fields are not edited before creation of the borrower, they
            willhave the following values by default :</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>for the ID : First letter of forename + surname.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>for the password: year of birth (yyyy) if it is entered,
                otherwise 0.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the possible personalised fields are displayed at the end of
            the borrower file. They allow you to add all types of information
            to a borrower file. For more information, consult the
            <emphasis>PMB Administrator's Guide</emphasis>,
            <emphasis>Borrowers</emphasis> chapter.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="circ_visu">
    <title>Display</title>

    <sect2 id="circ_visu_ex">
      <title>Copy by barcode</title>

      <para>Enter a barcode to display the information about the corresponding
      copy.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Circulation &gt; Display &gt; Copy by barcode; first
        screen</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/circ_visu_ex1.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <figure>
        <title>Circulation &gt; Display &gt; Copy by barcode ; results
        screen</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/circ_visu_ex2.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="circ_visu_rech">
      <title>Item by author/title</title>

      <para>You will see here a screen which works like the search section in
      the catalogue. (See later on the <emphasis>Catalogue</emphasis>
      chapter). You can enter a title or an author as the starting point of
      your search.</para>

      <para>Truncations are usable here, using regular expressions. To obtain
      more information about this subject, click on the link
      <emphasis>"regular expressions"</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>You can also search for an item by it's ISBN, it's commerce number
      (EAN), or as above, by it's copy number.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Circulation &gt; Display &gt; Item by author/title</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/circ_visu_doc.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="circ_resa">
    <title>Holds</title>

    <para>PMB allows the placing of hold requests on items for a borrower.
    Holds are available in the circulation tab in a borrower file (item loans)
    and, depending on the parameterisation, within the OPAC, from the borrower
    file. (For more information about parameterising the OPAC, consult the
    <emphasis>PMB Administrator's Guide</emphasis>.)</para>

    <para>Advanced hold management is available from PMB version 1.3
    onwards.</para>

    <sect2 id="circ_resa_encours">
      <title>in progress</title>

      <para>In this screen, current holds are displayed. The rank within the
      file is specified if many borrowers have held the same item.</para>

      <para>The holds are inserted as unvalidated. Once a hold has been added,
      the person responsible for the holds finds the corresponding items on
      the shelves, and holds (that is puts aside) these items. To edit the
      list of items to retrieve from the shelves, in the
      <emphasis>Editions</emphasis> tab, click on the menu item
      holds<emphasis> to process</emphasis>. (For more information, see <xref
      linkend="edit" />).</para>

      <para>The barcodes of the items which then put aside are scanned. The
      holds are then "validated".</para>

      <para>If you wish to delete a hold, Click the
      <emphasis>Delete</emphasis> option, then click on the button<emphasis>
      Validate the deletions</emphasis>.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Circulation &gt; Holds &gt; In progress</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/circ_resa_encours.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>You can print the relevant hold confirmation letters. To do this,
      click on the button <emphasis>Confirmation Letters</emphasis></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="circ_resa_depassee">
      <title>Expired</title>

      <para>The screen of expired holds lists the holds which were not
      cancelled and for which the valid until date is past. You must therefore
      delete them. To delete a hold, select the <emphasis>Delete</emphasis>
      option then click on the button<emphasis> Validate the
      deletions</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>You can, if you wish, leave additional time even with expired
      holds. In this case, do not delete the expired holds, until after the
      end of the extra time.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Circulation &gt; holds &gt; expired</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/circ_resa_depassees.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="circ_resa_docranger">
      <title>Items to shelve</title>

      <para>The list of items to shelve contains held documents, which have
      normally been removed from the shelves and held with the borrower name,
      and then the hold was deleted. The holds are placed, in most cases, at
      the library reception counter; "items to shelve" allows you to take
      stock of the times which must be reshelved.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Circulation &gt; holds &gt; to shelve</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/circ_resa_aranger.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>