<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="aide_contextuelle">
  <title lang="en">Contextual help</title>

  <para lang="en">Among the links located on the top right of the PMB
  management interface, the question mark "?" allows the display of PMB
  contextual help.</para>

  <figure>
    <title lang="en">Navigation links</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/barre-extra.gif" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang="en">The contextual help can be enabled or disabled by setting
  the PMB parameter with sub-type <emphasis>show_help</emphasis>. For more
  information, consult the <emphasis>PMB Administrator's
  Guide</emphasis>.</para>

  <sect1>
    <title lang="en">Availability of the contextual help</title>

    <para lang="en">The contextual help is available in French only at the
    moment. English, Italian and Spanish translations are in preparation. For
    more information, do not hesitate to ask about these versions, go to our
    news list: pmb.user@sigb.net (to subscribe send an e-mail to
    pmb.user_request@sigb.net with SUBSCRIBE in the subjectline.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title lang="en">How the contextual help works</title>

    <para lang="en">The contextual help is displayed in a pop-up. The help
    displayed corresponds to your management interface screen.</para>

    <figure>
      <title lang="en">The contextual help pop-up</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/aide-context-popup.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">The contextual help integrates the Administrator's Guide,
    the User's Guide and the Installation Guide within PMB.</para>

    <para lang="en">On top of every page, you have several elements :</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">the title of the chapter on screen</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">the section's title of the chapter on screen</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">navigation arrows enabling you to go from one page to
        another to browse the help.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <figure>
      <title lang="en">Contextual help, top page elements</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/aide-context-haut.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">At the bottom of each page, you will find various
    navigation icons.</para>

    <figure>
      <title lang="en">Contextual help, bottom page navigation icons</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/aide-context-bas.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">The left and right arrows enable you to browse the help by
    moving from one page to another.</para>

    <para lang="en">The top arrow is a link to the summary of the chapter on
    screen. Among the chapter titles of the User Guide, you can find the tabs
    Circulation, Cataloguing, Authority and Reporting.</para>

    <para lang="en">The "home" icon is a link to the summary of the currently
    displayed guide : the Administrator's Guide, the User's Guide and the
    Installation Guide.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title lang="en">Default operation</title>

    <para lang="en">Installing the contextual help is done by integrating a
    zip archive containing all of the documentation into the PMB install
    directory. It is available at <ulink
    url="http://www.sigb.net">www.sigb.net</ulink></para>

    <para lang="en">If the PMB administrator has not correctly installed the
    default contextual help, the link to the contextual help "?" will redirect
    you to the install files and to the settings found in the doc sub-folder
    of your PMB installation.</para>

    <para lang="en">In this case, contact your PMB administrator or read
    carefully the installation procedure. The latter is displayed in the
    pop-up under the links to the documentation files of the PMB
    installation.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>