<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="cat">
  <title lang='en'>Cataloguing</title>

  <para lang='en'>Cataloguing refers to the processes involved in the creation of a library catalogue, which in turn enables searches, loans management, the compilation of statistics, ...</para>

  <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Note </emphasis>Whenever you see a "basket" icon displayed in the Cataloguing tab, you can add an item (record, copy, bulletin) to a basket by clicking on the icon <graphic fileref="images/basket_small.gif" />.  For more information, see <xref linkend="cat_caddies" />.</para>

  <sect1 id="cat_ouvrages">
    <title lang='en'>Search</title>

    <sect2 id="cat_search">
      <title lang='en'>All records</title>

      <para lang='en'>Search "all records" includes all PMB records : monographs, serials main entries, analytical entries</para>

      <para lang='en'>Search "serials" is effected only on main entries for serials.</para>

      <para lang='en'>"Recent additions" allows you to display the latest entries in the database.</para>
      
      <para lang='en'>PMB allows the use of boolean operators in search expressions. For more information, see <xref linkend="exp_bool" />.</para>

      <sect3 id="cat_search_tit">
        <title lang='en'>Author/title</title>

        <sect4>
          <title lang='en'>Searching by title</title>

          <para lang='en'>The following screen appears when you click on the cataloguing tab. It allows searching and is always accessible in this module by clicking on "search" in the side menu.</para>

          <figure>
            <title lang='en'>cataloguing &gt; search &gt; search Author/title</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/cat_search_title.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para lang='en'>Let's search for the title "cat".</para>

          <para lang='en'>If you have installed the test database, the book <emphasis>Catfish Blues</emphasis> by <emphasis>Gérard Herzhaft</emphasis> is returned.</para>

          <figure>
            <title lang='en'>Search results</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/search_examp_1.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para lang='en'>To display the full bibliographical entry for a work returned by the search, click on "+" to expand the entry and list all the copies (electronic copies as well) of the work.</para>

          <para lang='en'>Click on the title to display the catalogue details of the work, and if necessary to make any desired modifications. The screen display shows the list of all the copies of the work.</para>

          <figure>
            <title lang='en'>List of copies of a work</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/liste-expl.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para lang='en'>To modify a record, click on <emphasis>Edit</emphasis>. To modify one of the copies of the work, click on its barcode. To add a copy, enter the <emphasis>item number </emphasis>then click on <emphasis>Add a copy</emphasis>. To add an electronic copy, click on <emphasis>Add an electronic copy</emphasis>. For more information, see <xref linkend="cat_isbd" />.</para>

          <para lang='en'>The details mentioned at the bottom of the catalogue entry relate to the copies of the work, their availability, etc. Click on a copy barcode to make any modification.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title lang='en'>Search by author, ISBN, EAN or item number</title>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Search by author</emphasis> works exactly like search by title.</para>

          <para lang='en'>You can also search for a document by its ISBN, commercial barcode (EAN) or item number.</para>

          <para lang='en'>Finally, you can refine your search by limiting it to specific document types.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="cat_search_categ">
        <title lang='en'>Subject/Class number</title>

        <para lang='en'>The available subject classes are displayed (you can modify them in the authority tab).</para>

        <para lang='en'>Click on the folder icon to open the subject class and possibly display the sub-classes.</para>

        <para lang='en'>When you have reached the desired class or sub-class, click on its name to display the results.</para>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; records &gt; search by subject/class number</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cat_search_categs.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="cat_search_terms">
        <title lang='en'>Keywords</title>

        <para lang='en'>Searching by keywords allows you to navigate amongst the thesaurus terms.</para>

        <para lang='en'><figure>
            <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; works &gt; search by keywords</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/cat_search_terms.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>To search by keywords, first enter one or more keywords you want to search, for example, <emphasis role="bold">history</emphasis>. The results are displayed in two areas in the central interface. The upper area displays subjects related to your search. Click on any one of them (for example <emphasis role="bold">political history</emphasis>) to display more details in the bottom area.</para>

        <para lang='en'>Click on the links to navigate from subject to subject.</para>

        <para lang='en'>To select a subject and display related works, click on the magnifying glass at the beginning of the line <graphic fileref="images/search_terms_select.gif" /> if the database does not contain any works under a keyword, the magnifying glass is not visible.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="cat_search_publisher">
        <title lang='en'>Publisher/Series</title>

        <para lang='en'>The Publisher/series search displays publishers and series exactly like the keywords search.</para>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; works &gt; search by publisher/series</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cat_search_publishers.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="cat_search_caddie">
        <title lang='en'>Baskets</title>

        <para lang='en'><emphasis>Search in</emphasis> &gt; <emphasis>Baskets</emphasis> allows to display the contents of a basket (also referred to as a "caddy"). Baskets correspond to a selection of records, bulletins or copies.</para>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; works &gt; search in baskets</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cat_search_paniers.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="cat_search_multi">
        <title lang='en'>Advanced search</title>

        <para lang='en'>Advanced search offers to search using a combination of various access points. You can select fields to search in &nbsp;: title, author, personalized search fields...</para>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>Works &gt; search &gt; advanced search</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/multicrit1.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para lang='en'>To start an advanced search :</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>Click on <emphasis>Add</emphasis> to define a first search criteria</para>

            <para lang='en'>Advanced search applies to access points of records, copies, periodicals and personalized fields.</para>

            <para lang='en'><figure>
                <title lang='en'>Available access points</title>

                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/multicrit2.gif" />
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>Next select a search type for the desired field, you can choose among "Booleean expression", "Contains one of the words", "Contains all the words", "Starts with", "Ends with", or "Exactly like". This type of search varies depending on the field selected<figure>
			
                <title lang='en'>Types of search in Title</title>

                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/multicrit_4.gif" />
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>If the field requires a value, enter it into the textbox; if it requires a choice (for example the type of media), click to select one or more options while maintaining the <emphasis>Ctrl</emphasis> key of your keyboard down.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>Finally click on <emphasis>Search</emphasis> to validate</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title id="exp_bool">Boolean Expressions</title>

        <para lang='en'>You can use boolean expressions with all the search screens. Boolean expressions were introduced in PMB with version 2.0.</para>

        <sect4>
          <title lang='en'>Simple search</title>

          <para lang='en'>By default, the engine looks for records containing <emphasis role="bold">at least</emphasis> (OR implicit) one of the words entered. Sorting is done by descending order on the number of word hits then alphabetically.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis>For example </emphasis><programlisting>cheddar cheese </programlisting> returns records containing the words cheddar OR cheese (Cheddar cheese, Red Leicester cheese, The history of the Cheddar region, ...). </para>

          <para lang='en'>Accented characters are ignored, uppercase words as well. If two words are separated by another sign other than space, +, or -, both words will appear in the search result.</para>

          <para lang='en'>For example <programlisting>Santa Cruz/sea</programlisting>will be analyzed as : find <emphasis>records containing Santa</emphasis> OR <emphasis>records containing Cruz AND sea</emphasis> OR <emphasis>both</emphasis>.</para>

          <para lang='en'>Some words are ignored because too frequent or having no significant meaning in English (e.g. : a, if, in, of, on, the, that, to, ...). They are referred to as stop words.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title lang='en'>The minus sign</title>

          <para lang='en'>The minus sign - is considered as an operator when placed in-between two words (see the chapter : Logical operators in-between words). Hence compound words must be surrounded by quotes for an exact term search, (see further below).</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title lang='en'>Truncation</title>

          <para lang='en'>Words can be truncated to the left, right or partially using the * sign.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis>For example </emphasis><programlisting>hor* </programlisting>will search for words starting with "hor" (horde, horizon, horse, ...),</para>

          <para lang='en'><programlisting>*logy</programlisting>will search for words ending with "logy" (psychology, theology, trilogy, ...),</para>

          <para lang='en'><programlisting>p*logy </programlisting>will search for words starting with "p" and ending with "logy" (psychology, paleonthology, pathology, ...).</para>

          <para lang='en'>Several truncations can be used within one and same word.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="cat_recherche_termesexacts">
          <title lang='en'>Searching exact terms</title>

          <para lang='en'>An exact term is defined as a text enclosed in quotation marks. Whenever the search engine encounters an exact term, it searches for records containing this term.
          
          <para lang='en'>Truncation can be used within exact terms.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis>For example </emphasis><programlisting>"dent"</programlisting>will return all records containing the term dent (dentist, accident, indentation, ...).</para>

          <para lang='en'>Exact term searching is convenient for search expressions containing spaces or punctuation marks. (an acronym for instance).

          <para lang='en'><emphasis>For example </emphasis><programlisting>"W.W.F."</programlisting> searches for records containing the text W.W.F.,</para>

          <para lang='en'><programlisting>W.W.F.</programlisting> searches for records containing the letters W or F.</para>

          <para lang='en'>Accents and uppercase are ignored in an exact term.</para>

          <para lang='en'>Finally exact terms can be used in all complex expressions as described further below.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title lang='en'>Negation</title>

          <para lang='en'>The "~" sign in front of a term represents the negation of the term. It actually means search for all records not containing that term.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis>for example </emphasis><programlisting>~work</programlisting> means all records except those containing the word "work"</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title lang='en'>Logical operators in-between two words</title>

          <para lang='en'>Logical operators can be used in-between words :</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>+ : AND operator</para>

              <para lang='en'><emphasis>For example </emphasis><programlisting>hard + disk</programlisting> means all records containing the words hard AND disk.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>- : NOT operator</para>

              <para lang='en'><emphasis>For example </emphasis><programlisting>hard - disk</programlisting> returns records containing the word disk, except those containing also the word hard.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para lang='en'>Several operators may be chained together in one and same equation or search expression. The precedence order applied is from left to right.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis>For example</emphasis> <programlisting>poetry + french - romantic*</programlisting> will return records containing poetry AND french NOT romantic(s).</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Caution</emphasis>, two operators cannot be placed immediately one after another, a negation cannot be combined with another operator (+~ expresses the same thing as the operator -).</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title lang='en'>Groupings</title>

          <para lang='en'>An expression can be grouped to become a single term. Groupings are made using parentheses. This makes it possible to change the order of precedence in the application of operators or to combine the results of complex search expressions or equations.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'><programlisting>poetry + (french romantic)</programlisting></para>

              <para lang='en'>means in all records containing the words french OR romantic, only those containing the word poetry.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'><programlisting>(french + poetry) romantic</programlisting>means means all records containing poetry AND french OR all records containing the word romantic</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'><programlisting>~(french + poetry) + (ameri* literature)</programlisting> means all records NOT containing the words poetry AND french AND records containing the words literature OR ameri*. Parentheses Parentheses can be imbricated with one another endlessly.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'><programlisting>(poetry + (french romantic)) (literature + XIX)</programlisting>means in all records containing french OR romantic, only those containing poetry OR records containing literature AND XIX</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title lang='en'>Relevance</title>

          <para lang='en'>Results are sorted by relevance and then alphabetically. Relevance is calculated simply on the total number of words or exact terms hits.</para>

          <para lang='en'>For example :</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>lobster maine will recall all records containing french OR poetry, those containing both words being displayed on top.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>~(french + poetry) (ameri* literature) will recall all records not containing poetry AND french, from these records, those containing literature OR ameri* appearing on top in the results (first literature AND ameri*, then ameri*, and finally literature)</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="cat_serial_search">
      <title lang='en'>Serials</title>

      <para lang='en'>For more details on Serials management, consult the section Serials &gt; New serial.</para>

      <para lang='en'>Search all records enables you to search the entire catalogue, including articles and serials.</para>

      <para lang='en'>Search serials allows you to recall a particular periodical entry immediately so you can add a newly received issue for example, or to resume the indexing of articles of a given issue.</para>

      <figure>
        <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; Serials &gt; Search</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cat_search_serials.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para lang='en'>PMB allows you to use regular expressions as search criterias. For more information, see <xref linkend="exp_bool" />.</para>

      <figure>
        <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; Serials &gt; Searcher, search results</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/resultats-recherche-perio.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para lang='en'>For more details on a search result, click on the "+" in front of the title.</para>

      <para lang='en'>To display a given serial, click on its title from among the search results. The serial entry is displayed on screen. For more information, consult the section 2.3.2 <emphasis>Displaying a serial.</emphasis></para>

      <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Note </emphasis>Only main entries of serials are displayed in the search results: for example, Newsweek, The Economist, Time; articles as well as the various issues of serials are not returned by a search but on the <emphasis>Issues</emphasis> screen, go to the section 2.3.3 <emphasis>Issues</emphasis>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title lang='en'>Recent additions</title>

      <para lang='en'>This element allows you to access the latest entries.</para>

      <figure>
        <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; Works &gt; recent additions</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cat_last.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para lang='en'>Recalling recently added records allows the librarian to rapidly find an entry for correction, for entering details not recorded previously...</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title lang='en'>Works</title>
  
    <sect2>
      <title lang='en'>New record</title>

      <sect3>
        <title lang='en'>Adding a new record</title>

        <para lang='en'>Adding a new record is a two-screen operation : first PMB asks for an identification number (ISBN), but it is not compulsory to enter it. If a EAN is entered, it is converted into an ISBN.</para>

        <sect4 id="cat_create">
          <title lang='en'>Entering ISBN, EAN or commercial number</title>

          <para lang='en'>If the identification number entered corresponds to an existing work in the database, the bibliographic record is opened in edit mode directly. This allows you to avoid the duplication of records when cataloguing.</para>

          <figure>
            <title lang='en'>Works &gt; New record</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/cat_new1.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para lang='en'>Then click on <emphasis>Next</emphasis> to continue to the next screen.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="cat_create_form">
          <title lang='en'>Entering data</title>

          <figure>
            <title lang='en'>Works &gt; New record (screen 2)</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/cat_new2.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <sect5>
            <title lang='en'>Choosing a material dsignation</title>

            <para lang='en'>In the drop down list at the top of the fill-in form, you can choose from among various material designations : </para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>printed text</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>manuscript text</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>musical score - printed</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>musical score - manuscript</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>cartographic document - printed</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>cartographic document - manuscript</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>video, projectable document</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>sound recording - non musical</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>sound recording - musical</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>2D graphical document</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>electronic document</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>multimedia document</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>3D object, artifact, ...</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para lang='en'>These material designations correspond to UNIMARC standards.</para>

            <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Warning</emphasis> : do not mistake them for media types which correspond to the copy.</para>
          </sect5>

          <sect5>
            <title lang='en'>Title entry</title>

            <para lang='en'>The title proper is the principal title of a work.</para>

            <para lang='en'>Even when the title is printed on the cover or on a section of the work, you must transcribe it from the title page as it is sometimes different from the cover title. In this case the cover title will be indicated elsewhere	(note zone).</para>

            <para lang='en'>You can also define the title proper of a different author, a parallel title and other title information.</para>

            <para lang='en'>Parallel titles are, for instance, titles of works in their original language.</para>

            <para lang='en'>Finally you can define collective titles. A collective title is a title common to various works of the same author. For example <emphasis>The Adventures of Flash Gordon</emphasis> by <emphasis>Alex Raymond</emphasis>. The field "Part of" is different from the "title" fields. To specify a title for a collection, click on the button "..."</para>

            <figure>
              <title lang='en'>Defining a collective title</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/titres_serie.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para lang='en'>Next select a title for the collection in the pop-up.</para>

            <figure>
              <title lang='en'>Collective title pop-up</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/popup-serie.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para lang='en'>If the title of your collection is not in the pop-up list, click on<emphasis> Add collection</emphasis>. Next enter the title, click on <emphasis>Save</emphasis> and finally select your collection from the list. You cannot modify or delete a collection in the pop-up. To do so, in the tab <emphasis>Authority</emphasis>, select <emphasis> collection</emphasis> in the menu. For more information, see <xref linkend="autorites" />.</para>

            <para lang='en'>The selected collection is then displayed in the record fill-in form.</para>

            <figure> 
              <title lang='en'>The selected collection is displayed</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/titres_serie2.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para lang='en'>To remove a selected collective title, click on the
			"X" button</para>

            <para lang='en'>You can also specify a <emphasis>part number</emphasis>.
			For instance, <emphasis>The Adventures of Flash Gordon</emphasis>, 
			number <emphasis>11</emphasis>.</para>
          </sect5>

          <sect5>
            <title lang='en'>Author entry (statement of responsibility)</title>

            <figure>
              <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; New record, selecting authors</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/cat_new_resp.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para lang='en'>To select an author, click on the button "..." then select the author in the search author pop-up. To search for an author, enter the first letters of his/her last name and click on  <emphasis>Search</emphasis>. The results of the search are then displayed.</para>

            <figure>
              <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; New record, select author pop-up</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/popup_authors.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para lang='en'>If the author of a work you are cataloguing is not yet registered,
			you can add him/her by clicking on the button <emphasis>Add author</emphasis>.</para>

            <figure>
              <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; New record, adding an author from the pop-up</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/popup-new-author.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para lang='en'>You can add a new author either during the cataloguing process or in the "authorities" tab. For more information on adding authors, see <xref linkend="autorites_ajout_auteur" />.</para>

            <figure>
              <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; New record, selected author</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/cat-new-resp-filled.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para lang='en'>If "author" is the appropriate term for the writer of a book, it is not the same thing for a film when the title of "Director" would be more appropriate. The term used then refers to the function of the author in relation to the type of work. To select a function (not mandatory), click on the button "...".</para>

            <figure>
              <title lang='en'>Select author function pop-up</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/popup-fonction.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para lang='en'>A few observations :</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>There can only be one primary author for a work, but there can be coauthors, and/or secondary authors. To select <emphasis>a coauthor<emphasis> or a <emphasis>secondary author</emphasis> click on the corresponding "..." button. To add an additional author, click on the "+" button.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>to remove an author or a function, click on the "X" button</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </sect5>

          <sect5>
            <title lang='en'>Publisher entry, series, sub-series and collective titles</title>

            <figure>
              <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; New record, Imprint, series</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/cat_new_publisher.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para lang='en'>Entries for series, sub-series, and collective titles are made when creating or editing records (data entry only), or in the Authority tab. Start with <emphasis>sub-series</emphasis> if necessary, otherwise <emphasis>series</emphasis> or finally<emphasis>publisher</emphasis>.</para>

            <para lang='en'>In the select sub-series pop-up, select a sub-series <emphasis>or else</emphasis> click on <emphasis>Add sub-series</emphasis>, fill-in the known fields then click on the select "mother" series button of the sub-series.</para>

            <para lang='en'>In the select series pop-up containing our sub-series, select a series <emphasis>or</emphasis> choose <emphasis>Add series</emphasis>, fill-in the known fields except the publisher, then click on the select publisher button.</para>

            <para lang='en'>In the select publisher pop-up, select a publisher <emphasis>or </emphasis>choose <emphasis>Add publisher</emphasis> and complete the entry.</para>

            <para lang='en'>Once the entry is completed, select the publisher of the series, then the series containing our sub-series, and finally save the sub-series and select it.</para>

            <para lang='en'>In general, choose the more specific element first. Choose the sub-series, then the series and in the end the publisher.</para>

            <para lang='en'>A series corresponds to a publishers' choice : <emphasis>Penguin Books, Rough Guide</emphasis> series</para>

            <para lang='en'>A sub-series answers to the same concern but at a higher level: Oxford University Press, Oxford Handbooks 8, sub-series History.</para>

            <para lang='en'>A collection is a work published in a set of volumes under a collective title, each volume bearing its own title.</para>

            <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Example</emphasis> Tolkien, J.R.R. <emphasis role="bold">Collective title</emphasis> The Lord of the Rings <emphasis role="bold">part Number</emphasis> Book III <emphasis role="bold">Title proper</emphasis> The Return of the King</para>

            <para lang='en'>To make this entry, you must first create the collection and the collective title in PMB before selecting them. The part number and the title proper must be entered when creating the record of the work.</para>
          </sect5>

          <sect5>
            <title lang='en'>ISBN, EAN or commercial number</title>

            <para lang='en'>The ISBN, which was asked in the first screen of the new record entry, is displayed here. Click on the "..." button to open a pop-up either for scanning the EAN of the work or for entering its ISBN. The entry is done via a pop-up to avoid closing a new record entry in edit mode after validation of a barcode scan.</para>

            <para lang='en'>PMB automatically converts EANs (commercial barcodes) into ISBN.</para>

            <figure>
              <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; New record, ISBN area</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/cat_new_isbn.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </sect5>

          <sect5>
            <title lang='en'>Collation</title>

            <para lang='en'>The collation area details various information related to the physical aspect of the document : extent of item (number of volumes, pagination), illustrations, format, price, accompanying materials.</para>

            <figure>
              <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; New record, Collation area</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/cat_new_collation.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </sect5>

          <sect5>
            <title lang='en'>Notes</title>

            <para lang='en'>There are three types of notes : <emphasis>General</emphasis>, <emphasis>Contents</emphasis>-linked (critical appraisal), and <emphasis>a Summary, an Excerpt </emphasis>of the document (for instance, the summary of a novel on the outside back cover).</para>

            <figure>
              <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; New record, Notes area</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/cat_new_notes.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </sect5>

          <sect5>
            <title lang='en'>Indexing</title>

            <para lang='en'>The indexing area is made up of three elements :</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Subject headings</emphasis> : add
				a subject from the PMB internal thesaurus. For more information about
				subject headings, see <xref linkend="autorites_categ" /> .</para>

                <para lang='en'>To select a subject, click on the "..." button. To enter an additional subject, click on the "+" button. To remove a selected subject, click on the "X" button.</para>

                <figure>
                  <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; New record, select subject pop-up</title>

                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="images/cat_new_categ.gif" />
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para lang='en'>To create a subject heading, click on the Add button.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Classification</emphasis> : adding a
				class number. For more information, consult the chapter <emphasis>Authority</emphasis>, section <emphasis>Classification</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Free indexing</emphasis> : here you can freely enter keywords, separated by spaces. You can, for instance, specify keywords, or use the index a thesaurus not integrated into PMB (Sears subject headings, for example).
				</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <figure>
              <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; New record, Indexing area</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/cat_new_indexation.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </sect5>

          <sect5>
            <title lang='en'>Language of publication</title>

            <para lang='en'>Here you can specify the original language of the publication, defined by default in the user's preferences. For more information, consult the chapter <emphasis>User preferences</emphasis>.</para>

            <para lang='en'>The language codes are defined by the UNIMARC standard.</para>

            <para lang='en'>If the document is a translation, you can define the original language.</para>

            <figure>
              <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; New record, Language of publication area</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/cat_new_langue.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </sect5>

          <sect5>
            <title lang='en'>Links (electronic ressources)</title>

            <para lang='en'>The associated URL must be entered fully (including http://) to ensure that the link will function with any internet browser.</para>

            <para lang='en'>The electronic format can be chosen freely by the cataloguer. Prefer field entries using the term "file", for instance "PDF file" or "Acrobat File", and generic indications such as : "internet site".</para>

            <figure>
              <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; New record, Links area</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/cat_new_liens.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Advanced : RSS feeds</emphasis>. You can also link an RSS feed to a record. An RSS feed is a round-the-clock information flux broadcasted by an internet site. The RSS feeds of the BBC news site, news.bbc.co.uk, bring you the latest headlines of the site. By tying an RSS feed to an entry describing the BBC news site, you enable the readers of your library or documentation centre to access the latest BBC news from your OPAC.</para>

            <para lang='en'>To link an RSS feed, enter the corresponding URL (you can easily find the information on the web) into the associated URL field. Enter RSS NN as the electronic format, NN being a number in minutes defining the news refresh rate. For example, if you enter "RSS 30", the corresponding RSS feeds will be refreshed every 30 minutes. These information will be cached, accelerating the PMB OPAC responses for the next 30 minutes.</para>
          </sect5>

          <sect5>
            <title lang='en'>Custom fields</title>

            <para lang='en'>Finally, at the bottom of the record you can define your custom fields.</para>

            <para lang='en'>The customizable fields of records contain additional information, you can create them in <emphasis>Administration</emphasis> &gt; <emphasis>Records</emphasis> &gt; <emphasis>Customizable</emphasis>. For more information, consult the <emphasis>Administrator's Guide</emphasis>, chapter <emphasis>Records</emphasis>.</para>

            <para lang='en'>If no custom fields were defined, this area will not be displayed.</para>

            <figure>
              <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; New record, Custom fields area</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/cat_new_perso.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </sect5>

          <para lang='en'>Once the various fields of the record are filled, click on <emphasis>Save</emphasis>. The record is saved, and you come to the list of copies of the document.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="cat_isdbd">
        <title lang='en'>List of copies of a document</title>

        <para lang='en'>The next screen shows the ISBN formatted record together with corresponding copies, if any.</para>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; Works, list of copies of a document</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/liste-expls.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para lang='en'>To modify a record, click on <emphasis>Edit</emphasis>. The modification and creation operations	open the same screen.</para>

        <para lang='en'>You can <emphasis>Add a copy.</emphasis></para>

        <para lang='en'>You can also <emphasis>Add an electronic document</emphasis>.</para>

        <para lang='en'>If the record already contains copies, you can edit them by clicking on the copies' number.</para>

        <para lang='en'>If the record already contains electronic copies, you can display and modify them. To display e-copies click on the icon, to modify them click on the title.</para>

        <sect4>
          <title lang='en'>Modifying a record</title>

          <para lang='en'>To modify a record, click on the "Edit" button at the bottom of the entry just above above the associated copies list.</para>

          <para lang='en'>In edit mode a record displays the same fill-in form as a new record's (consult the section 1.2.1.2,  Adding a new record). However you will also find additional buttons at the bottom of the screen.</para>

          <figure>
            <title lang='en'>Buttons available at the bottom of the "Modifying a record" screen</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/cat_modif_notice.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <sect5>
            <title lang='en'>Replace with</title>

            <para lang='en'>Makes it possible to replace a record by another, this allows you to remove duplicates and gather copies linked with various double entries.</para>
          </sect5>

          <sect5>
            <title lang='en'>Duplicate</title>

            <para lang='en'>Allows the duplication of a record. A new record is displayed, enter changes to be made on the original entry relevant to the document being catalogued and save the new record.</para>

            <para lang='en'>This function is very useful for cataloguing complete series or collections.</para>
          </sect5>

          <sect5>
            <title lang='en'>Hist.</title>

            <para lang='en'>This button is displayed only when the audit of records and copies is enabled. It makes it possible to see the name of the user who made the catalogue entry, and who made any modifications. The information is displayed in a pop-up and depends on the audit type level. For more information, consult the PMB Administrator's Guide, Tools, Parameters, type_audit in "General Parameters".</para>

            <figure>
              <title lang='en'>History</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/cat_hist_notices.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </sect5>

          <sect5>
            <title lang='en'>Z39.50</title>

            <para lang='en'>Allows you to search for a record using the Z39.50 search function. This button launches a new search on the ISBN of the displayed record.</para>
          </sect5>

          <sect5>
            <title lang='en'>Delete</title>

            <para lang='en'>Allows you to delete a record. Warning, you	can delete a record only if it does not have any associated copies (hard or electronic).</para>
          </sect5>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="cat_expl_create">
          <title lang='en'>Adding a new copy</title>

          <para lang='en'>To modify one of the copies of the document, click on its barcode. To add a copy, enter the <emphasis>item number</emphasis> then click on  <emphasis>Add a copy</emphasis>.</para>

          <figure>
            <title lang='en'>Adding a new copy : entering the item number</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ajout-expl.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para lang='en'>The <emphasis>item number </emphasis>is the barcode you placed on the cover, if you are using a barcode reader. Else it is then a distinct number given to every item of your library (accession number).</para>

          <figure>
            <title lang='en'>Add a copy</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/ajout-expl-2.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para lang='en'>The "add a copy" screen allows you to enter various data:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>the <emphasis role="bold">item number</emphasis> is displayed. This data is <emphasis role="bold">mandatory</emphasis>. To modify it click on the "..." button and scan the barcode number of the copy into the pop-up (or enter a new item number then validate).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>enter a<emphasis role="bold">call number</emphasis>. This information is <emphasis role="bold">mandatory</emphasis>. The call number is often made up of the decimal notation followed by the first three letters of the author's name.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>select the <emphasis role="bold">media type </emphasis>in the drop-down list. The list of the document types is configurable in <emphasis>Administration &gt; Items &gt; Media types</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>select the <emphasis role="bold">location </emphasis>in the drop-down list. The location list is configurable in <emphasis>Administration &gt; Items &gt; Locations</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>select the <emphasis role="bold">section</emphasis> in the drop-down list. The sections list is configurable in <emphasis>Administration &gt; Items &gt; Sections</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>select the<emphasis role="bold">owner</emphasis> of the copy in the drop-down list. The owners list is configurable in <emphasis> Administration &gt; Items &gt; Owners</emphasis>. Generally, it is your library's holdings. However you can have a deposit from your main County Public Library or from another library.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>select the <emphasis role="bold">status</emphasis> of the copy in the drop-down list. The status list is configurable in <emphasis>Administration &gt; Items &gt; Status </emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>select the <emphasis role="bold">statistical code </emphasis>of the copy in the drop-down list.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>you can also define for <emphasis role="bold">notes</emphasis> a message related to the copy. This message will be displayed before any loan. For example : "ASSIMIL method, please check that the case contains 3 cds".</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>finally you can define a price.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para lang='en'>Some of these entry fields can have default values defined in your <emphasis>user preferences</emphasis>. For more information, consult the chapter
		  <emphasis>User preferences</emphasis>.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis>Below price </emphasis>are located <emphasis role="bold">the custom fields </emphasis>of the copy. They represent additional data that you can define in <emphasis>Administration &gt; Items &gt; Customization.</emphasis> For more information, consult the <emphasis>PMB administrator's Guide, Copies</emphasis>.</para>

          <para lang='en'>To save your modifications click on <emphasis>Save</emphasis> else <emphasis>Cancel</emphasis>. If you have opened a copy in edit mode you can also <emphasis>Delete </emphasis>it.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="cat_explnum_create">
          <title lang='en'>Adding an electronic copy</title>

          <para lang='en'>Electronic copies or e-copies are not links, but actual digital documents directly integrated in your catalogue in PMB. You can thus add to your catalogue as many types of digitized documents : PDF, MP3, text, spreadsheet, pictures...</para>

          <figure>
            <title lang='en'>Adding an e-copy</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/doc_num_new.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para lang='en'>You can define various information :</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>the <emphasis role="bold">name</emphasis> of the document</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>the <emphasis role="bold">file</emphasis> of the digital document. Click on the button <emphasis>Browse</emphasis> and select the file you wish to upload to the server.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">a thumbnail</emphasis> (the image for
			  the electronic document icon). Click on the button <emphasis>Browse</emphasis> 
			  and select the file you wish to upload to the server.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>you can also upload an external file from your intranet or the internet. In this case specify <emphasis role="bold">the URL </emphasis>of the file.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para lang='en'>PMB generates thumbnails automatically from GIF, PDF, JPG and PNG files, and uses the appropriate icons for most of the file formats.</para>

          <para lang='en'>To save your modifications click on <emphasis>Save</emphasis> else <emphasis>Delete</emphasis>. If you have opened an e-copy in edit mode, you can also <emphasis>Delete </emphasis>it.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="cat_edit_expl">
          <title lang='en'>Modifying a copy</title>

          <para lang='en'>Modification and add screens are almost identical, the former has two additional buttons : Hist. and Delete.</para>

          <sect5>
            <title lang='en'>Hist.</title>

            <para lang='en'>This button is displayed only when the audit of records and copies is enabled. It makes it possible to see the name of the user who made the catalogue entry, and who made any modifications. The information is displayed in a pop-up and depends on the audit type level. For more information, consult the PMB Administrator's Guide, Tools, Parameters, type_audit in "General Parameters".</para>
          </sect5>

          <sect5>
            <title lang='en'>Delete</title>

            <para lang='en'>Allows you to delete the displayed copy. Warning, a copy cannot be deleted if it is currently on loan.</para>
          </sect5>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title lang='en'>Modifying an e-copy</title>

          <para lang='en'>The modification screen of an e-copy is identical to the add an electronic copy screen.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
      
      <sect3>
        <title lang='en'>Cataloguuing special records</title>

        <para lang='en'>PMB allows you to catalogue not only books and periodicals, but also your multimedia kits, websites, RSS fluxes...</para>

        <sect4>
          <title lang='en'>Cataloguing a website</title>

          <para lang='en'>To catalogue a website, define the material designation as <emphasis role="bold">electronic document</emphasis>. Enter a title proper for your record. In the <emphasis role="">links (electronic resources)</emphasis> area, enter the associated URL (use the format <emphasis role="bold">http://www.bbc.co.uk< emphasis>). In electronic format for this resource, you can enter <emphasis role="bold">website</emphasis>.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title lang='en'>Cataloguing an RSS flux</title>

          <para lang='en'><remark><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis> PMB can also generate an RSS flux from a basket or a virtual shelf. You can load a basket by means of the Selective Dissemination of Information (SDI). For more details on adding an RSS flux, consult <xref linkend="dsi_rss_def" />.</remark></para>

          <para lang='en'>"<emphasis>An RSS feed, acronym for Really Simple Syndication or Rich Site Summary is a format for syndicating Website contents. The system is used by news-oriented websites and weblogs to publish their headlines and web-contents enabling users to consult them immediately without having to visit the websites themselves</emphasis>" (source : http://http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RSS).</para> 

          <para lang='en'>To catalogue an RSS, enter a title for the RSS feed. In links, copy-paste the URL of the RSS feed. In electronic format for this resource, enter "RSS ### #" with :</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>RSS : for PMB to display the web-contents of the URL, enter the XML file correctly</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>### : for the cache period, enter 30 for 30 minutes, for instance</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'># : 0 or 1 to publish the RSS feed on the Home page or not</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para lang='en'>To display RSS feeds on the OPAC Home page, define the parameter <emphasis>opac show_rss_browser</emphasis> 1. For more information on customizing PMB, consult the <emphasis>PMB Administrator's Guide, Tools</emphasis>.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="cat_serial">
    <title lang='en'>Serials</title>

    <para lang='en'>PMB allows the entry of general information about periodicals; for instance, details regarding the most recent issue or articles in the issue.</para>

    <sect2 id="cat_serial_vocabulary">
      <title lang='en'>Vocabulary</title>

      <para lang='en'>By serials we mean any publication (including non-print material) generally appearing at regular or irregular intervals under a uniform title.</para>

      <para lang='en'>You need to know the meaning of four terms to understand how PMB manages serials :</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">the serial </emphasis> is defined in PMB by a record (called <emphasis role="bold">"mother" record </emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">main entry</emphasis>) establishing the title of the publication, of the magazine, etc. This record describes the serial or periodical on a general level : <emphasis>Le Monde </emphasis>is a daily newspaper, founded by <emphasis>Beuve-Méry</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">the issue</emphasis> (also called <emphasis role="bold">bulletin</emphasis>) identifies, for instance, the issue numbered <emphasis>32478</emphasis> dated <emphasis>15 August 2002</emphasis>of <emphasis>Le Monde</emphasis>. Cataloguing a periodical means describing all the individual issues and associated copies so they can be loaned or analytical entries of articles can be made.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">the copy</emphasis> corresponds to the physical aspect of an issue. If you have two subscriptions to Le Monde, you'll have in your holdings <emphasis>two copies</emphasis> of the issue numbered<emphasis>32478</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">the article</emphasis> (also called <emphasis role="bold">content</emphasis>) forms the basis of the various issues of a periodical. Articles can be described and catalogued, and therefore can be described in a record. For example : an article published on page 10 of Le Monde, 18 June 2003, can be catalogued.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Let's recap</emphasis> : We subscribe to the daily Le Monde (a <emphasis role="">periodical entry </emphasis>), with an <emphasis>issue</emphasis>) numbered 32478 of which we possess two copies in the library (<emphasis>two items</emphasis> with two distinct barcode numbers for loans). In the issue, there are fifty major articles that the readers and librarians can search independently, each one relating to the corresponding issue and to the availability of the corresponding copies.</para>

      <para lang='en'>If no entry exists in PMB yet, the periodical article entry is made in a few different steps : add a new periodical entry, list current issues, create copies if any, make an analytical entry for the article.</para>

      <figure>
        <title lang='en'>Browsing the display screens of periodicals</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/navig-bulletinage.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para lang='en'>When you display the record entry of a periodical (here <emphasis>Géo</emphasis>), of one of its issues (here issue number<emphasis>278</emphasis>) or of one of the articles of this issue, a navigation bar is appears on top of the screen. This bar allows you to rapidly go to the upper level in the periodical record exploration.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="cat_serial_form">
      <title lang='en'>New serial</title>

      <figure>
        <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; Serials &gt; New serial</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cat_new_serial.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <sect3 id="cat_serial_add">
        <title lang='en'>Adding a serial</title>

        <para lang='en'>Let's describe in detail how to add a new serial. In the <emphasis>Cataloguing</emphasis> tab, click on <emphasis>New serial</emphasis> in the side menu.</para>

        <sect4>
          <title lang='en'>Material designation</title>

          <para lang='en'>PMB can manage various serials formats. The printed form (newspapers, magazines, reviews) is the most common, but PMB can also manage talking newspapers for the blind and visually impaired persons, electronic periodicals, etc.</para>

          <para lang='en'>The 13 formats of the drop-down list are normalized to UNIMARC standards :</para>


                  <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>printed text</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>manuscript text</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>musical score - printed</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>musical score - manuscript</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>cartographic document - printed</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>cartographic document - manuscript</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>video, projectable document</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>sound recording - non musical</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>sound recording - musical</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>2D graphical document</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>electronic document</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>multimedia document</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'>3D object, artifact, ...</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title lang='en'>Other entry fields</title>

          <para lang='en'>The other entry fields for a periodical correspond to those of a work. See above section 1.2.1 <emphasis>Adding a new record</emphasis>.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis> It is not possible to define collation (number of pages, accompanying materials, ...) for a periodical. Similarly the notion of series does not apply for periodicals.</para>

          <para lang='en'>After saving your periodical record, you get the screen <emphasis>Serials: Display items</emphasis>.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="cat_serial_view">
        <title lang='en'>Displaying a serial</title>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>Displaying a serial</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/visu-periodique.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para lang='en'>From this screen you can modify the periodical record by clicking on the <emphasis role="bold">Edit</emphasis> button. Modifying a periodical entry is similar to adding a new periodiacl. See below the section <emphasis>New serial</emphasis>.</para>

        <para lang='en'>You can <emphasis role="bold">Delete</emphasis> the periodical.</para>

        <para lang='en'>You can <emphasis role="bold">add an issue</emphasis> as well.</para>

        <para lang='en'>In the <emphasis>list of issues</emphasis> displayed underneath the main entry in the lower half of the screen, each line shows for a given issue the <emphasis role="bold">Issue number</emphasis>, the <emphasis role="bold">Date of issue or period</emphasis>, the number of articles <emphasis role="bold">Art</emphasis>, the number of <emphasis role="bold">E-copies</emphasis>, and the number of <emphasis role="bold">Hardcopies</emphasis></para>

        <para lang='en'>You can display an issue by clicking on any one line in <emphasis>the list of issues</emphasis>. The issue is then displayed on the screen <emphasis>Serials: issue(s)</emphasis>.</para>

        <sect4 id="cat_serial_bul">
          <title lang='en'>Adding a new issue</title>

          <para lang='en'>Only the following data are required : the issue number (32478), the issue barcode, the period and/or date of issue, and finally the title of the issue.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Numbering</emphasis> : is used to store the issue number. For instance the number <emphasis>153</emphasis> of the periodical.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Barcode</emphasis> : it allows you to enter the issue barcode, for example <emphasis>3792578022009</emphasis>.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Date of issue</emphasis> is used to enter the date of publication of the issue (01/06/04). The date is used as sorting order for the display of issues. If no date is entered, either manually or using the calendar pop-up by clicking on <emphasis>calendar,</emphasis> PMB will automatically fill it with the current date.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Period entry field</emphasis> : this field is used to enter the publication date as printed on the issue : for example<emphasis> June-July 2006</emphasis>.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Title of issue</emphasis> : it is used to enter the title of a given issue, for example <emphasis> special : climate change</emphasis>.</para>

          <figure>
            <title lang='en'>Adding an issue</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/numero.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="cat_serial_bul_view">
          <title lang='en'>Managing issues</title>

          <figure>
            <title lang='en'>Managing issues</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/bulletinage.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para lang='en'>From this screen you can :</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Modify</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">Delete </emphasis> the issue</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>Modify a copy in the issues' list of copies by clicking on its barcode</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>Display an e-copy by clicking on its icon, or modify it by clicking on its title</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'>Add a copy by entering its copy number and clicking on <emphasis role="bold">Add a copy</emphasis></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Add an e-copy</emphasis></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Add an article entry</emphasis> to the issue</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para lang='en'>The list of articles is displayed in the lower half the screen.</para>

          <para lang='en'>For more details, click the "<emphasis role="bold">+</emphasis>" icon at the start of the line.</para>

          <para lang='en'>To modify an article entry click on its title.</para>

          <para lang='en'>To add an electronic document to an article click on the <emphasis role="bold">Add an eletronic document</emphasis> button located in the article details.</para>

          <sect5 id="cat_serial_expl">
            <title lang='en'>Adding a copy to an issue</title>

            <para lang='en'>See above the section 1.2.2.1 on how to create a copy of a document <emphasis>Adding a copy </emphasis>. Adding copies to an issue is similar.</para>
          </sect5>

          <sect5 id="cat_serial_explnum">
            <title lang='en'>Adding an e-copy to an issue</title>

            <para lang='en'>See above the section 1.2.2.2 on how to create an electronic document <emphasis>Adding an electronic document</emphasis>. Adding e-copies to an issue is similar.</para>
          </sect5>

          <sect5 id="cat_serial_analysis">
            <title lang='en'>Adding articles</title>

            <para lang='en'>The article record corresponds to a standard record but with an additional feature: pagination.</para>

            <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis> : You cannot add a title proper from another author to an article.</para>

            <para lang='en'>Cataloguers are advised to follow the following conventions :
			</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">p. X</emphasis> article on page X</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">pp. X-Y</emphasis> article from pages X to Y</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">pp. X-Y, Z, AA-AC</emphasis> article separated in three groups of pages : from pages X to Y, on page Z, from  pages AA to AC</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para lang='en'>To these conventions, it is also possible to add column information, generally by specifying col. then a, b or c for the column position.</para>
          </sect5>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="cat_caddies">
    <title lang='en'>Baskets</title>

    <para lang='en'>The baskets are PMB storage space : you can fill them with
	records, bulletins (issues of a periodical), copies.</para>

    <para lang='en'>In PMB the baskets permit the checking of the holdings, for inventory
	purposes. They also allow the clearance of the holdings, when works are
	too old or too deteriorated.</para>

    <para lang='en'>The baskets permit the storage of a bibliography : the results of multiple
	searches for a publication, a thematical catalog,...</para>

    <para lang='en'>There are two ways to fill a basket :  by entering elements manually
	(look for the basket icon), or by scanning/entering the bar code.</para>

    <sect2 id="cat_caddie_gestion">
      <title lang='en'>management</title>

      <para lang='en'>By default, in the Baskets/Management part, the screen displays the baskets
	  management. You can display the procedures management via the "Procedures management"
	  link.</para>

      <sect3 id="cat_caddie_gestion_caddie">
        <title lang='en'>Baskets management</title>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>cataloguing &gt; Baskets &gt; Management &gt; Baskets management</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cat_paniers_gestion.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para lang='en'>You can see the content of a basket by clicking on its name.
		By clicking on Modify, you can modify its content : name, format,
		comment, access rights. Finally, by clicking on Add a basket you
		can define a new basket.</para>

        <sect4>
          <title lang='en'>Basket content</title>

          <para lang='en'>You can consult the content of a basket by clicking on its name.</para>

          <figure>
            <title lang='en'>cataloguing &gt; Baskets &gt; Management &gt; Basket
			management, basket content</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/cat_paniers_gestion2.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para lang='en'>You can delete its elements by clicking on its
		  Delete icon :<graphic
          fileref="images/basket_del.gif" /></para>

          <para lang='en'>A basket can contain elements from the holdings
		  (records, PMB cataloged works or bulletins) :</para>

          <figure>
            <title lang='en'>Holdings elements</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/cat_paniers_gestion_known.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para lang='en'>If you unfold the note by clicking on the "+" sign
		  located in front of the element, you will be able to consult
		  the ISBN formatted note as well as the works and digital
		  copies list. The note display and search results display are
		  similar (cataloguing &gt; Search).</para>

          <para lang='en'>However, when preparing the basket you may have scanned
		  an item not belonging to your holdings (for example a book belonging to the
		  County Public Library, and that was not imported into BMP). To help you keep tracks
		  of these items, a basket can also contain unknown items :</para>

          <figure>
            <title lang='en'>Unknown items</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/cat_paniers_gestion_unknown.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para lang='en'>In a basket content, the elements already checked
		 are highlighted by an icon preceding their titles. For more information
		 about basket items checking, consult the section <xref linkend="cat_caddie_pointage" />.</para>

          <figure>
            <title lang='en'>Checked item</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/cat_paniers_gestion_pointe.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="catalogue_panier_editer_un_panier">
          <title id="catalogue_panier_editer_un_panier.title">Modifying a basket</title>

          <para lang='en'>You can also modify a basket by clicking on the link
		  Modify on the right side of the screen.</para>

          <figure>
            <title lang='en'>cataloguing &gt; Baskets &gt; Management &gt;
			Baskets management</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/cat_paniers_editer_un_panier.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para lang='en'>The "Modify a basket" screen allows you to modify the name and
		  comment of a basket as well as the users access rights to this basket.</para>

          <para lang='en'>You can see the basket type : notes basket, bulletins basket,
		  copies baskets. You cannot change the type of an existing basket. If
		  you have made a mistake creating it, delete it and create a new one.</para>

          <para lang='en'>Under the "Access granted to" heading, you can see
		  boxes corresponding to the access rights. The names displayed are 
		  the PMB authorized users. You cannot cancel the administrator's rights.</para>

          <para lang='en'>You can thus create a basket which will only be accessible to
		  you (and the administrator).</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title lang='en'>Adding a basket</title>

          <para lang='en'>The "Add a basket" screen is identical to the "Modify a basket" screen.
		  The only difference is the presence of the Delete button. For more information,
		  consult above the <xref linkend="catalogue_panier_editer_un_panier" />section.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title lang='en'>The PMB default baskets installed at start-up</title>

          <para lang='en'>If your data base administrator has installed PMB with the
		  "essential data for a quick start" (feed_essential.sql,
          for more informations, see the PMB Installation Guide), 
		  a few baskets are already created, they serve as examples or for 
		  the facilitating of the library management. </para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis>Notes for exhibition</emphasis> notes basket
		  example. It has been designed for receiving the notes for a small exhibition,
		  which can later be highlighted thanks to the OPAC virtual shelves,
		  for more informations consult <xref
          linkend="cat_etg" /></para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis>Notes for return to the County Public Library</emphasis>
		  Easing management notes basket. It has been designed for receiving the bibliographic
		  notes of the works returned to the County Public Library ; for
		  data base clearance purposes after the returns.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis>Copies for return to the County Public Library</emphasis>
		  Easing management copies basket. It has been designed for receiving the copies
		  returned to the County Central Library ; you will thus be able
		  to get them out of the loan and clean your data base.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis>Notes in doubles by title</emphasis> Easing management 
		  notes basket. It will receive the doubles ; for
		  data base clearance purposes.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis>Never loaned</emphasis> 
		  Items basket to facilitate management. It will receive the
		  items that were never loaned.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="cat_caddie_gestion_procs">
        <title lang='en'>Procedures management</title>

        <para lang='en'>This screen displays the procedures associated with the baskets.
		You can define procedures that will fill the  baskets, check those
		already made up or apply changes to the notes, bulletins or copies
		stored in the basket.</para>

        <para lang='en'>For more information about the procedures (several examples are provided),
		consult further along the <emphasis>3.5 basket use examples </emphasis>section.</para>

        <sect4>
          <title lang='en'>By default procedures installed at PMB start-up</title>

          <para lang='en'>If your data base administrator has installed PMB with the
		  "essential data for a quick start" (feed_essential.sql,
          for more information, see the PMB Installation Guide), then
		  several procedures are already created. They serve as examples or for 
		  the facilitating of the library management..</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis>EXPL by section / owner</emphasis> selection
		  procedure by one or more sections for one or more owners.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis>EXPL where the classification starts with</emphasis>
		  selection procedure by the first characters of a classification.
		  Useful for the holdings periodical checking.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis>Copies for return to the County Central Library</emphasis>
		  action procedure allowing a status change for all the copies of a basket.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis>Notes by author</emphasis>
		  notes selection procedure by one or more authors.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis>Notes in doubles</emphasis>
		  selection procedure by doubles according to the title.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis>Notes without works</emphasis> 
		 selection procedure for notes having no works/items attached.</para>

          <para lang='en'><emphasis>Never loaned</emphasis> 
		  selection procedure for works never loaned.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="cat_caddie_collecte">
      <title lang='en'>Basket filling</title>

      <figure>
        <title lang='en'>cataloguing &gt; Baskets &gt; Basket filling</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cat_paniers_collecte.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para lang='en'>You can fill a basket via a bar code reader (by scanning
	  the works bar code). You also can input elements in a basket by
	  starting a selection procedure.</para>

      <para lang='en'>These procedures were defined in Baskets/Management/ Procedures management.</para>

      <para lang='en'>At any time in the Cataloguing tab, when you see a basket shaped icon,
	  you can add an element (note, copy, bulletin) to a basket by clicking on
	  the icon <graphic
      fileref="images/basket_small.gif" /></para>

      <sect3>
        <title lang='en'>subtleties of the additions to a basket</title>

        <para lang='en'>Managing the additions of elements to a basket
		corresponds to the various operating modes :</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>adding a <emphasis role="bold">note</emphasis> to a
            <emphasis>copies basket</emphasis> = adding
            <emphasis>all the note copies</emphasis> to the
            basket</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>adding a <emphasis role="bold">copy</emphasis> to a
            <emphasis>notes basket</emphasis> = adding the 
            <emphasis>copy note </emphasis> to the basket</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>adding an <emphasis role="bold">analytical note
            </emphasis>to a <emphasis>bulletins basket</emphasis>= adding
            the <emphasis>corresponding analyzed bulletin</emphasis> to
			the basket</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para lang='en'>Caution : adding a <emphasis
        role="bold">bulletin</emphasis>to a <emphasis>notes basket
        </emphasis>will be <emphasis>without effect</emphasis>. Indeed,
		two types of notes correspond to a bulletin : the periodical mother
		note and the analytical notes of the bulletin.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="cat_caddie_pointage">
      <title lang='en'>Checking</title>

      <para lang='en'>Basket checking permits the comparison of a basket content with
	  other elements, either by manual checking (scanning) or by starting
	  a PMB selection procedure.</para>

      <sect3 id="cat_caddie_pointage_douchette">
        <title lang='en'>Checking with bar code reader</title>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>cataloguing &gt; Baskets &gt; with bar code reader</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cat_paniers_collecte_douchett.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para lang='en'>Click on the name of the basket you want to check.<figure>
            <title lang='en'>cataloguing &gt; Baskets &gt; Checking &gt; with bar code reader</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/cat_paniers_collecte_douchett2.gif" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="cat_caddie_pointage_sélection">
        <title lang='en'>Checking by selection</title>

        <para lang='en'>To check a basket, click on it.</para>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; Baskets &gt; Checking &gt; By
          selection</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/panier_pointage_select.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para lang='en'>Then click on the procedure you want to use.</para>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; Baskets &gt; Checking &gt; By selection,
          choice of the checking procedure</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/panier_pointage_select2.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para lang='en'>Do not forget to adjust the values of the parameters, if any.</para>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; Baskets &gt; Checking &gt; By selection,
          checking completed</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/panier_pointage_select3.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para lang='en'>The basket elements that were checked are declared as being
		<emphasis> Checked</emphasis>. The total number of elements in the basket is
		shown. The elements belonging to the holdings registered in PMB are displayed
		on the second line of the summary table, bottom of the page.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="cat_caddie_actions">
      <title lang='en'>actions</title>

      <figure>
        <title lang='en'>cataloguing &gt; Baskets &gt; Actions</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cat_paniers_actions.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para lang='en'>From this screen, you can do the following :</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>Modify the content (HTML, Excel HTML, Excel
          XLS formats).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>empty the selected basket</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>delete the basket elements from the data base</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>export the content of the basket</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>transfer the content of a basket into another one</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>apply an SQL query to the content of a basket</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para lang='en'>You can perform these actions by clicking on their corresponding
	  links in the central interface, then by clicking on the basket name you want
	  to affect.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title lang='en'>Editions</title>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>cataloguing &gt; Baskets &gt; Actions &gt; Editions</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cat_paniers_edition.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para lang='en'>For more information on the PMB export formats,
		consult the<emphasis> Administrator Guide</emphasis>, Chapter
        10 <emphasis>Export</emphasis>, section 1 <emphasis>File formats.</emphasis></para>

        <para lang='en'>Select then the concerned basket elements : checked or unchecked elements.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title lang='en'>Emptying the basket</title>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>cataloguing &gt; Baskets &gt; Actions &gt; Emptying the basket</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cat_paniers_vider_panier.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para lang='en'><emphasis>Emptying the basket </emphasis>allows to empty a basket content.</para>

        <para lang='en'>Select then the concerned basket elements : checked or unchecked elements</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title lang='en'>Deleting from the data base</title>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>cataloguing &gt; Baskets &gt; Actions &gt; Deleting from the data base</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cat_paniers_suppr_base.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para lang='en'>Deleting from the data base means deleting the selected basket elements
		(notes, bulletins or copies) from the library data base.</para>

        <para lang='en'>Use it with extreme caution, for example to delete a lost works basket.</para>

        <para lang='en'>Select then the concerned basket elements : checked or unchecked elements.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title lang='en'>Export</title>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>cataloguing &gt; Baskets &gt; Actions &gt; Export</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cat_paniers_export.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para lang='en'>Export allows exporting a basket content.</para>

        <para lang='en'>Select the concerned basket elements then: checked or unchecked elements.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title lang='en'>Transfer</title>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>cataloguing &gt; Baskets &gt; Actions &gt; Transfer</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cat_paniers_transfert.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para lang='en'>Transfer allows transfering basket elements (checked or unchecked)
		into another basket.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title lang='en'>By query</title>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>cataloguing &gt; Baskets &gt; Actions &gt; By query</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cat_paniers_requete.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para lang='en'>You can also apply an SQL query to a basket content ; for
		example an UPDATE query (for more information about queries,
		consult the <emphasis>PMB Administrator Guide</emphasis>) will
		change the classification of a set of books that were
		displaced in your library.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title lang='en'>using baskets examples</title>

      <para lang='en'>A few examples on how to use baskets. These examples will allow you
	  to better comprehend the use of PMB baskets along with their powerful
	  features via the queries.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title lang='en'>Putting works without any copies into a basket</title>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>Create a notes basket,</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>Create a selection procedure, enter the following
			code (CAUTION, without any line break) :</para>

            <programlisting>SELECT notice_id as object_id, 'NOTI' as object_type FROM notices left join exemplaires on notice_id=expl_notice WHERE expl_notice is null and niveau_biblio='m' and niveau_hierar='0'</programlisting>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>Go to basket &gt; Basket filling &gt; By selection and fill your basket with
			this procedure</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title lang='en'>Inventory management</title>

        <para lang='en'>&gt; I would like to simplify my inventory operations,
		I thus &gt; created a basket with all the copies of a section. I
		 &gt; will then be able to physically check all the works of a shelf
		 and with &gt; the "Delete from the basket the checked elements" action I
		 will be able to find the books &gt; that are in the data base but are
		 physically lost, stolen... &gt; &gt; I wanted to use a procedure but
		 I am a real dummy! In the &gt; PS I have the inventory of all my 
		 documentaries but I don't know &gt; how to transform it so it works
		 in the baskets &gt; Here is the corrected PS ! select expl_id as object_id, 'EXPL' as
        object_type from exemplaires, notices, docs_section where idsection in
        (!!section!!) and expl_notice=notice_id and expl_section=idsection
        order by section_libelle, expl_cote, expl_cb 
		All that is left to do is to set a value for the !!section!! parameter : a multiple choice list
		from a query with : select idsection,
        section_libelle from docs_section order by section_libelle &gt;
        Stephanie FORT &gt; Librarian &gt; &gt; CDI - Collège Saint
        Pierre &gt; Jette (Belgique)</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="cat_etg">
    <title lang='en'>Shelves</title>

    <para lang='en'>The virtual shelves are a set of notes baskets that may or may not
	contain notes. The virtual shelves allow you to display these notes in the
	OPAC or on your web site. Thanks to this feature, PMB permits the display on 
	your web site, of virtual exhibitions, lists of your latest library
	purchases, readers club books selection, etc ...</para>

    <sect2 id="cat_etg_gestion">
      <title lang='en'>Management</title>

      <para lang='en'>The shelves management displays a list of all the existing shelves.</para>

      <figure>
        <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; Shelves &gt; Management</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cat_etg_gest.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para lang='en'>You can add a shelf by clicking on the
      <emphasis>Add a shelf</emphasis> button.</para>

      <para lang='en'>To modify an existing shelf, click on its
	  corresponding line.</para>

      <para lang='en'>A shelf is defined by its name, a validity period, and
	  its visibility on the OPAC home page. A comment can also be added.
	  Finally each shelf has its own access rights : they allow authorized users
	  to modify the selected shelf and its content.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="cat_etg_constit">
      <title lang='en'>Assembling</title>

      <para lang='en'>The assembling screen of a shelf makes it possible to add or
	  remove the content of one or more baskets from one of your virtual shelves.</para>

      <para lang='en'>Click on the shelf you wish to assemble.</para>

      <figure>
        <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; Shelves &gt; Assembling</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cat_etg_constitution.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para lang='en'>Then check the notes baskets you wish to add to your virtual
	  shelf.</para>

      <figure>
        <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; Shelves &gt; Assembling, adding baskets to
		a shelf</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cat_etg_constitution2.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para lang='en'>Then click on  <emphasis>Save</emphasis> to validate the assembling
	  of your virtual shelf.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title lang='en'>Z39.50</title>

    <sect2 id="cat_z3950">
      <title lang='en'>Z39.50 Search</title>

      <para lang='en'>The Z39.50 search permits searching a work in the
	  catalog of another library and its direct insertion into the PMB catalog,
	  without having to repeat the cataloguing operations already done
	  by the other library.</para>

      <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Comment</emphasis> the records
	  represent an intellectual creation and are protected by copyright. The 
	  records of the <emphasis>Library of Congress</emphasis>
	  as well as those of the <emphasis>French National Library</emphasis>
	  are in the public domain : you can freely inport them. Other libraries
	  may have different policies. Contact them for more information.</para>

      <figure>
        <title lang='en'>cataloguing &gt; Z39.50 &gt; Search</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cat_z39_search.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para lang='en'>Let's take an example, and import <emphasis>Germinal</emphasis> from
      <emphasis>Zola</emphasis>. As search criteria, we select "title" and in the 
	  adjacent field we enter "Germinal".</para>

      <para lang='en'>We then select one or more libraries which will possibly
	  have a copy of <emphasis>Germinal</emphasis>, document we want to add
	  to our catalog.</para>

      <figure>
        <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; Z39.50 &gt; Search, intermediate screen showing
		progress</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cat_z39_progress.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para lang='en'>When a request has not given any results after a wait period of a dozen of seconds,
	  we can imagine that our internet connection is saturated, that
	  the server is too busy to answer, or that our PMB configuration is not
	  correct (if all of our z39.50 searches have not returned any results so far).</para>

      <para lang='en'>The lines starting with "Failure..." correspond to an error. An
	  error message is then displayed. Here, a few examples :</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>Timeout : the server did not answer before the end of the predetermined
		  time interval</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>Connect failed : the server has answered but the connection failed
		  </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>Malformed query : the z3950 perfil of the server is not correct.
          Contact your data base administrator about the z3950 perfil</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para lang='en'>The lines starting with TERMINE indicate that the search
	  was succesfull. The number of results is indicated in the
	  <emphasis> the server returned X notes out of Y found </emphasis>
	  sentence (limitation to the first hundred notes, if you get more
	  than a hundred results, refine your search).</para>

      <para lang='en'>Once the search is completed, click on "Results" to display 
	  the corresponding results.</para>

      <figure>
        <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; Z39.50 &gt; Search, search results screen</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cat_z39_results.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para lang='en'>A screen displays the search results then. The results list
	  shows summarized notes, ISBD format. Notes that were otherwise
	  entered and other minor informations do not appear on this list. To select
	  a note, click on its title.</para>

      <figure>
        <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; Z39.50 &gt; Search, notes modification screen before
		insertion</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cat_z39_integrer.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para lang='en'>The resulting note is displayed in a "modifying screen" so you can consult
	  it in details, modify it and insert it into the catalog. There are a few differences
	  with the regular "Modifying a note" screen : the authors and publishers have 
	  two entry fields corresponding to the principal element (last name) and the hooked-in
	  element (first name). Once you have made the modifications, validate
	  them by clicking on the "insert into the note" button.</para>

      <para lang='en'>The following screen allows you to define copies then.</para>

      <figure>
        <title lang='en'>Cataloguing &gt; Z39.50 &gt; Search, copies entry screen</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cat_z39_expl.jpg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para lang='en'>Cataloguing your copies then. Once a copy has been defined, click on
	  Inserting. You can also return to the results list and insert
	  an additional result.</para>

      <para lang='en'>On top of this screen, there is the heading "integrated note",
	  with a link<emphasis> See it in cataloguing.</emphasis> The note is displayed
	  in its modification screen. This screen is the same as the  "record
	  creation" screen (see above the <emphasis>New note</emphasis> section).</para>

      <sect3>
        <title lang='en'>Daily use of the Z39.50 search</title>

        <para lang='en'>For the French libraries, the Z39.50 search main interest
		is the ISBN search of the French National Library (BnF). As for
		the works of your holdings, you can easily catalog/classify them
		by scanning their commercial bar code (EAN) with your bar code reader.</para>

        <para lang='en'>To do so,</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>go to cataloguing &gt; Z39.50 &gt; Search</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>select BnF among the servers,</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>make sure that the search criteria is ISBN</para>

            <figure>
              <title lang='en'>cataloguing &gt; Z39.50 &gt; Search, ISBN search</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/cat_z39_search_isbn.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>enter/scan your work bar code into the input field. The scanned EAN
			(commercial code) will be converted into an ISBN code by PMB.</para>

            <figure>
              <title lang='en'>cataloguing &gt; Z39.50 &gt; Search, ISBN search</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/cat_z39_results_isbn.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>The ISBN search result is normally unique. Theoretically,
			no two works can have the same ISBN code. However, bibliographic
			notes can be more or less detailed according to the selected server.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para lang='en'>You can then look for copies of the searched work, and continue.</para>

        <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Comment </emphasis>: the BnF has a turnaround for
		cataloguing operations. The latest publications (published less than a year ago)
		may not still be cataloged.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>