<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="circ">
  <title>Circulation of the items</title>

  <para>The circulation of the items in a library means the management of the
  copies owned by the library and their communication with the readers. We
  often refer to these as loan operations.</para>

  <para>The vertical menu of the circulation tab contains 3 headings :
  Circulation, Display and Holds. In the Circulation section you can manage
  the readers and the loans. The Display section retrieves information about
  the items in the library. Finally, the Holds section allows you to manage
  the holds placed by the readers.</para>

  <sect1 id="circ_circ">
    <title>Circulation</title>

    <sect2 id="circ_pret">
      <title>Loan Items</title>

      <para>The loaning of items is very simple and can be carried out
      completely using a barcode reader. It is enough to enter the barcode of
      the reader's membership card, then that of the borrowed items. The
      barcode reader replaces the entry of the barcode and the pressing of hte
      "enter" button on the keyboard.</para>

      <para>Naturally, there must already be some items and borrowers entered
      into the database for loans to be permitted.</para>

      <sect3 id="circ_pret_1">
        <title>Borrower Search</title>

        <para>The creation of a borrower and thier card is explained
        later.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Circulation &gt; Loan Items</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/circ_pret.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="circ_pret_2">
        <title>Search results</title>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Example</emphasis> lending
        <emphasis>Rwanda : a people with a history</emphasis>, by <emphasis>C.
        M. Overdulve</emphasis>, to our borrower <emphasis>Luke Skywalker
        </emphasis>(barcode of their membership card is 100003).</para>

        <para>His barcode is entered or read by the barcode reader to identify
        the borrower.</para>

        <para>It is also possible to enter all or part of the borrower's name
        to in order to select them from a list. Here we will enter the letter
        "s" for Skywalker.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Circulation &gt; Loan (results of a borrower search)</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/circ_pret_2.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Click in the search results list on the borrower
        Skywalker.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="circ_lecteur">
        <title>Borrower Card</title>

        <figure>
          <title>Circulation &gt; Loan (borower card)</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/circ_pret_3.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The barcode of a copy of Rwanda is 33700003286792.</para>

        <para>It is sufficient to enter this barcode in the "new loan" field
        to issue the loan. Enter and check the barcode. The loan is then added
        to the list of current loans.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Circulation &gt; Loan, loan added</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/circ_pret_4.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>You can then cancel the loan by clicking on cancel (in this
        case, the loan is not included within the statistics, compared to a
        loan immediately followed by a return).</para>

        <para>You can also print a loan ticket. It takes the form of a PDF
        file generated by PMB. Under Windows, the "print loan ticket" button
        requires the Acrobat browser plugin and will display a printable loan
        ticket detailing the borrower, the copy loaned, and the date the item
        is due for return. It is suffucient therefore to click on the Acrobat
        print icon to print this loan ticket.</para>

        <para>The launching of Acrobat to view the loan ticket may sometimes
        be slow, according to your machine. In this case, either be patient,
        or launch Acrobat in advance.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Example of a loan ticket.</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/circ_pret_ticket.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis> If your item has a
        particular status which does not allow lending, but this rule can be
        overridden, PMB will ask you if you want to force the loan or
        not.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Copy is not loanable: option to force the loan</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/pret_exclu.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>In our example, the library parameters (name, address, logo) are
        configured for the Bueil Library. These parameters are configurable in
        the administration tab. For more information, consult the
        <emphasis>PMB Administrator's Guide</emphasis>,
        <emphasis>Utils</emphasis> section.</para>

        <para>Other available functions from the reader file::</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Update the borrower's information (also possible to renew
            their subscription), see creating a borrower, later in this
            document.</para>

            <para>To modify the borrower's information, click on the
            <emphasis>update</emphasis> button.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Renew an existing loan</para>

            <para>To renew a loan, click on the due date button. In the
            calendar popup which will open, select the new due date. In this
            popup, use the arrows to move forward or backward a month, and the
            double arrows to move by year.</para>

            <figure>
              <title>Date selection Popup for renewing a loan</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/prolonger_pret_popup.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Delete the borrower : only possible if the borrower has no
            current loans. If there are current loans, their return must be
            carried out prior to deletion.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Print the loan record: Printing the list of borrowed items
            and current holds.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Print the borrower card</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Create a new borrower</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The add hold button allows the hold of an item.</para>

            <para>After having clicked on add a hold, you can carry out a
            search. When the item to be held is found, click on its title to
            insert it into the list of holds.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="circ_retour">
      <title>Return items</title>

      <para>Scan the barcode of the item being returned. The borrower card is
      not required.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Circulation &gt; Return items</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/circ_retour.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>A confirmation message is displayed to allow you to check that the
      barcode does correspond to the item being returned.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Circulation &gt; Return items, confirmation of a processed
        return</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/circ_retour2.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>This display gives the borrower name that returned the item.
      Following this is a link which allows access to the relevant borrower
      file, which can be used, for example, to issue new loans.</para>

      <para>Also displayed are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the item type, location, class mark and other copy
          details</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the return is overdue, the number of days late</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The name of the borrower who had the item on loan</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If entered, any message associated with the item</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Any pending holds</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="circ_groups">
      <title>Borrower Groups</title>

      <para>The <emphasis>Borrower groups </emphasis>functionality allows PMB
      to be used by librarians who wish to manage their borrowers by groups:
      classes, familles, etc.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Circulation &gt; Borrower Groups</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/circ_groupes.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="circ_emprcreate">
      <title>New Borrower</title>

      <sect3 id="circ_emprcreate_1">
        <title>Barcode for the new borrower</title>

        <para>A borrower barcode is required whenever you want to create a new
        borrower. I<emphasis>f the pmb.num_carte_auto</emphasis> parameter is
        active (has a value of 1), PMB will suggest a new borrower barcode
        equivalant to the highest barcode in the database +1.</para>

        <para>For more information about the PMB parameters, consult the
        <emphasis>PMB Administrator's Guide</emphasis>, Utils section.</para>

        <para>Once a borrower card number has been defined, click to reach the
        data entry screen for new borrower information.</para>

        <para>Note: Validation (Click on the next button) is automatic with a
        barcode reader.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="circ_emprcreate_2">
        <title>Enter the borrower data</title>

        <para>You can enter the personal information about the borrower on
        this screen.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Circulation &gt; New Borrower</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/circ_nouveau.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>If personnalisable fields were defined in
        <emphasis>Administration &gt; Bororwers &gt; Personalisable
        Parameters</emphasis>, they will be visible at the bottom of the
        borrower file. On the following screen, you can complete the required
        personalisable parameters. To enter a different barcode, replace with
        the barcode of your choice or rescan the new barcode.</para>

        <para>If you enter a barcode which is already allocated, PMB will give
        you an error message.</para>

        <para>To ntoe :</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A surname must always be entered</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A forename must always be entered</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The date of birth is not mandatory if the parameter
            empr.birthdate_optional is selected (has a value of 1). For more
            information, consult the <emphasis>PMB Administrator's
            Guide</emphasis>, <emphasis>Utils</emphasis> chapter,
            <emphasis>Parameters</emphasis> section.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The fields <emphasis>OPAC ID</emphasis> and <emphasis>OPAC
            password</emphasis> define the login ID the borrower can use in
            the OPAC (normally situated at the left of the screen). If these
            fields are not edited before creation of the borrower, they
            willhave the following values by default :</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>for the ID : First letter of forename + surname.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>for the password: year of birth (yyyy) if it is entered,
                otherwise 0.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the possible personalised fields are displayed at the end of
            the borrower file. They allow you to add all types of information
            to a borrower file. For more information, consult the
            <emphasis>PMB Administrator's Guide</emphasis>,
            <emphasis>Borrowers</emphasis> chapter.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="circ_visu">
    <title>Display</title>

    <sect2 id="circ_visu_ex">
      <title>Copy by barcode</title>

      <para>Enter a barcode to display the information about the corresponding
      copy.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Circulation &gt; Display &gt; Copy by barcode; first
        screen</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/circ_visu_ex1.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <figure>
        <title>Circulation &gt; Display &gt; Copy by barcode ; results
        screen</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/circ_visu_ex2.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="circ_visu_rech">
      <title>Item by author/title</title>

      <para>You will see here a screen which works like the search section in
      the catalogue. (See later on the <emphasis>Catalogue</emphasis>
      chapter). You can enter a title or an author as the starting point of
      your search.</para>

      <para>Truncations are usable here, using regular expressions. To obtain
      more information about this subject, click on the link
      <emphasis>"regular expressions"</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>You can also search for an item by it's ISBN, it's commerce number
      (EAN), or as above, by it's copy number.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Circulation &gt; Display &gt; Item by author/title</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/circ_visu_doc.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="circ_resa">
    <title>Holds</title>

    <para>PMB allows the placing of hold requests on items for a borrower.
    Holds are available in the circulation tab in a borrower file (item loans)
    and, depending on the parameterisation, within the OPAC, from the borrower
    file. (For more information about parameterising the OPAC, consult the
    <emphasis>PMB Administrator's Guide</emphasis>.)</para>

    <para>Advanced hold management is available from PMB version 1.3
    onwards.</para>

    <sect2 id="circ_resa_encours">
      <title>in progress</title>

      <para>In this screen, current holds are displayed. The rank within the
      file is specified if many borrowers have held the same item.</para>

      <para>The holds are inserted as unvalidated. Once a hold has been added,
      the person responsible for the holds finds the corresponding items on
      the shelves, and holds (that is puts aside) these items. To edit the
      list of items to retrieve from the shelves, in the
      <emphasis>Editions</emphasis> tab, click on the menu item
      holds<emphasis> to process</emphasis>. (For more information, see <xref
      linkend="edit" />).</para>

      <para>The barcodes of the items which then put aside are scanned. The
      holds are then "validated".</para>

      <para>If you wish to delete a hold, Click the
      <emphasis>Delete</emphasis> option, then click on the button<emphasis>
      Validate the deletions</emphasis>.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Circulation &gt; Holds &gt; In progress</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/circ_resa_encours.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>You can print the relevant hold confirmation letters. To do this,
      click on the button <emphasis>Confirmation Letters</emphasis></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="circ_resa_depassee">
      <title>Expired</title>

      <para>The screen of expired holds lists the holds which were not
      cancelled and for which the valid until date is past. You must therefore
      delete them. To delete a hold, select the <emphasis>Delete</emphasis>
      option then click on the button<emphasis> Validate the
      deletions</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>You can, if you wish, leave additional time even with expired
      holds. In this case, do not delete the expired holds, until after the
      end of the extra time.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Circulation &gt; holds &gt; expired</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/circ_resa_depassees.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="circ_resa_docranger">
      <title>Items to shelve</title>

      <para>The list of items to shelve contains held documents, which have
      normally been removed from the shelves and held with the borrower name,
      and then the hold was deleted. The holds are placed, in most cases, at
      the library reception counter; "items to shelve" allows you to take
      stock of the times which must be reshelved.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Circulation &gt; holds &gt; to shelve</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/circ_resa_aranger.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>