<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="principes">
  <title lang='en'>General Principles</title>

  <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Ergonomics relating to the use of a web
  application</emphasis></para>

  <para lang='en'>PMB is a web application, a "WebApp". Running on a web server (see the
  <emphasis>PMB Installation Guide</emphasis>, Section 1,
  <emphasis>Installation on Windows,</emphasis> for more information about
  Apache), PMB benefits from the flexibility of internet applications.</para>

  <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Do not use the "previous page" browser
  button.</emphasis></para>

  <para lang='en'>"Previous page" and "Page forward" allow the movement from one page to
  another on the internet, it works the same way with PMB.</para>

  <para lang='en'><graphic fileref="images/warning.gif" /><emphasis role=""><emphasis
  role="bold">Warning.</emphasis></emphasis> Whenever you see on your screen a
  message starting with <emphasis>Update </emphasis>do not click on previous
  page. Whenever you see this message, it is vital to let the update to
  run until completion. In general, avoid using previous page if you can achieve
  the same results by clicking on one of the links visible on screen.</para>

  <para lang='en'>The "Reload" button of your browser enables you to reload the page
  displayed on screen.</para>

  <para lang='en'>Whenever you reload a page usually the result of an entry form (for example
  adding a new volume), the data is submitted again to the server.</para>

  <para lang='en'>Following the same principle as "Previous page", your browser's "Stop"
  button interrupts the loading of a page.</para>

  <figure>
    <title lang='en'>Mozilla navigation buttons - Previous page, Page forward, Reload,
    Stop</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/back_mozilla1.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <figure>
    <title lang='en'>Mozilla navigation buttons - Previous page, Page forward, Reload,
    Stop</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/back_mozilla2.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <figure>
    <title lang='en'>Internet Explorer navigation buttons - Previous page, Page forward,
    Stop, Reload</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/back_ie.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Warning</emphasis> When carrying out important operations on the database (additions, deletions), you should not stop the page loading,you would be interrupting the update in progress and putting at risk the integrity of the database.</para>

  <para lang='en'>In particular, never click "cancel" when the database is being
  restored, backed-up or optimized.</para>
</chapter>