<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="useropac">
  <title>The OPAC module</title>

  <para>OPAC stands for <emphasis role="bold">O</emphasis>nline <emphasis
  role="bold">P</emphasis>ublic <emphasis role="bold">A</emphasis>ccess
  <emphasis role="bold">C</emphasis>atalogue. The OPAC module allows readers
  to carry out a search in the library catalogue.</para>

  <para>In fact, the PMB OPAC module is a WebPAC : an OPAC accessible via the
  Web.</para>

  <para><emphasis>How to configure</emphasis> the OPAC is described in the
  <emphasis>PMB Administrator's Guide</emphasis>.</para>

  <para>The OPAC can be separate from the PMB management interface, and placed
  on a separate server. For more information about installing the OPAC consult
  the <emphasis>PMB Installation Guide</emphasis>.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis> this chapter isn't the OPAC
  help, but only a quick aide-memoire. A <emphasis>Guide to the PMB OPAC
  </emphasis>is currently in preparation.</para>

  <sect1 id="useropac_access">
    <title>Accessing the OPAC</title>

    <para>The OPAC catalogue of the PMB-managed library will be accessible by
    default at the following internet address :</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">[v1.3 to 2.1]</emphasis> <emphasis
    role="bold">http://localhost/pmb/opac_css</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">[v1.0 to 1.2]</emphasis>
    http://localhost/phpmybibli/opac_css</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">[pre-v1]</emphasis>
    http://localhost/phpmybibli/opac</para>

    <para>However, for the other workstations on a local network, you need to
    replace <emphasis>localhost</emphasis> by the network name of the PMB
    server.</para>

    <para>To obtain this name under Windows, right-click on <emphasis>My
    Computer</emphasis> then select <emphasis>Network ID</emphasis>. You will
    then be shown the name of the machine on the local network.</para>

    <para>The online catalogue produced by PMB is dynamic: It is automatically
    updated at each reload of the page. Therefore an update made in the
    management interface (see following sections) is reflected immediately. A
    newly catalogued item is also accessible immediately in the OPAC.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="useropac_interface">
    <title>The OPAC Interface</title>

    <para>The PMB OPAC displays 3 main areas of information on the
    screen</para>

    <figure>
      <title>OPAC welcome screen</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/opac_home.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A "search" dialogue area is found at the top of the page.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">New</emphasis> : Starting with version
        1.3, the OPAC offers an advanced search feature.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Subject headings are presented in the bottom right area. Other
        blocks can also be displayed. The OPAC is highly customizable. For
        more information, consult the<emphasis> Administrator's Guide
        ,</emphasis> <emphasis>Tools</emphasis> chapter,
        <emphasis>Parameters</emphasis> section.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The left column (which can be deactivated from
        <emphasis>Administration &gt; Tools &gt; Parameters</emphasis>) offers
        the possibility to identify the barcode of the reader and the address
        of your library. The library's addresss is parameterisable
        in<emphasis> Administration</emphasis> &gt; <emphasis>Tools</emphasis>
        &gt; <emphasis>Parameters</emphasis> (For more information consult the
        PMB Administrator's Guide, Utils chapter).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="useropac_keywords">
    <title>Key word search</title>

    <para>If you enter a term in the "Search" textbox, the OPAC will display
    the results of your search. You can further refine your search by checking
    or unchecking the boxes which correspond to the elements queried : title,
    author, series...</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">New</emphasis> : Starting with version 1.3,
    the PMB OPAC stores all your searches made throughout the duration of your
    session (from the start of your connection, that is to say, the first OPAC
    window opened by you).</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="useropac_categs">
    <title>Browsing the subject index</title>

    <para>Conceived to facilitate the exploration of resources, the subject
    index corresponds to a thesaurus with a hierarchical structure ready to be
    loaded (by you) with subject terms to be usable in PMB.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="useropac_lecteur">
    <title>Accessing readers' accounts from the OPAC</title>

    <para>Readers registered in the management interface can access their
    account from the OPAC. For that, they need their reader's barcode (or
    identifier), printed on their library card, and their password as
    well.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis> : by default this password is
    identical to the reader's barcode. It can be changed in the management
    interface, or at any time by the reader by accessing his account in the
    OPAC.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>OPAC reader file</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/opac_fiche_empr.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect1>
</chapter>