<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="acquis">
  <title lang='en'>Acquisitions</title>

  <para lang='en'>The <emphasis>Acquisitions</emphasis> tab in PMB enables you to prepare, and subsequently place your orders. You can also organize your orders under budgetary lines so you can monitor your budget.</para>

  <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Warning</emphasis> To display the acquisitions tab you have to </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para lang='en'>enable the parameter type <emphasis>acquisitions</emphasis>: set the sub-type <emphasis>active</emphasis> to 1. For more details consult the <emphasis>PMB Administrator's Guide, chapter Tools, section Parameters</emphasis>.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para lang='en'>grant the appropriate access privileges to the current user for him/her to use the <emphasis>acquisitions</emphasis> tab. For more details, consult the <emphasis>PMB Administrator's Guide, chapter Users</emphasis></para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Prerequisites</emphasis> To use the <emphasis>acquisitions</emphasis> tab, you need to define various parameters first : name of library, financial year, budget... For more details consult the <emphasis>PMB Administrator's Guide, chapter Acquisitions</emphasis>.</para>

  <para lang='en'>Readers' and library staff suggestions are also accessible from the <emphasis>acquisitions</emphasis> tab.</para>

  <sect1 id="acquis_achats">
    <title lang='en'>Purchases</title>

    <sect2 id="acquis_achats_commandes">
      <title lang='en'>Orders</title>

      <remark><emphasis role="bold">Prerequisites </emphasis>Before you can create an order, you need first to define one supplier at least. For more details go to the section <emphasis>Supplier</emphasis> below.</remark>

      <para lang='en'>You can create an order, or recall and modify an existing order.</para>

      <para lang='en'>Orders can have four different status, accessible via the drop down list</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>all : display all orders</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>outstanding : awaiting validation</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>current</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>settled</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>filed</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para lang='en'>To create an order, click on the button <emphasis role="bold">Add order</emphasis>.</para>

      <remark>If you have more than one library defined, select the one concerned by the order</remark>

      <para lang='en'>To modify an order, recall it and click on name.</para>

      <para lang='en'>Similarly to print an order, click on the <emphasis>Print</emphasis> icon from the list of orders.</para>

      <figure>
        <title lang='en'>Acquisitions &gt; Orders, Orders list</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/acquisition-liste-commandes.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <sect3 id="acquis_achats_commandes_infos">
        <title lang='en'>General informations</title>

        <para lang='en'></para>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>Acquisitions &gt; Orders, selecting a supplier</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/acquistions-choix-fournisseur.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para lang='en'>To select a <emphasis role="bold">supplier</emphasis>, click on the "<emphasis role="bold">...</emphasis>" pop-up button. Once a supplier is selected, click on the <emphasis role="bold">+</emphasis> icon under his name in front of <emphasis role="bold">Main address</emphasis>. to display his business details.</para>

        <para lang='en'>The <emphasis role="bold">delivery</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">billing</emphasis> addresses of the library concerned by your order are similarly displayed on the screen.</para>

        <para lang='en'>You can define <emphasis role="bold">notes</emphasis>. These will not be printed on the order form, but may only be consulted on screen. You can use them, for instance, to provide your colleagues with any information related to the order.</para>

        <para lang='en'>You can also define <emphasis role="bold">notes for print </emphasis> on the purchase order. These notes are addressed to your supplier and may contain any additional instructions regarding the order.</para>

        <para lang='en'>Whenever you create or subsequently modify an order you can define a <emphasis role="bold">supplier's quotation number</emphasis>, a <emphasis role="bold">date of payment</emphasis> as well as a <emphasis role="bold">payment number</emphasis>.</para>

        <para lang='en'>The <emphasis role="bold">currency used </emphasis> (for example €) corresponds to the default value of parameter <emphasis>gestion_devise</emphasis> in <emphasis>General parameters</emphasis>. For more information, consult the <emphasis>PMB Administrator's Guide, chapter Tools, section Parameters</emphasis>.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="acquis_achats_commandes_lignes">
        <title lang='en'>Adding or modifying an item on order</title>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>Adding an item</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/acquisition-commande-nouvelle-ligne2.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para lang='en'>A document on order is defined by a <emphasis role="bold">code</emphasis> (ISBN, Barcode, Commercial No). Here you can scan the barcode of the item to order</para>

        <para lang='en'>Next enter <emphasis role="bold">Title/Author/ Publisher/Series</emphasis>. To facilitate reading, you are advised to <emphasis>Enter</emphasis> (carriage return) each detail on a new line. If the item exists already in the database, <emphasis role="bold">Title/Author/ Publisher/Series</emphasis> will be entered automatically.</para>

        <para lang='en'>You can also modify the quantity ordered (<emphasis role="bold">Qty</emphasis>), and definir a <emphasis role="bold">price (tax inclusive)</emphasis>as well.</para>

        <para lang='en'>In the column <emphasis role="bold">Delivery date</emphasis>, define a scheduled delivery date using the format DD/MM/YYYY. For this you can use the date type button under the heading Delivery date. The button dusplays a calendar in a pop-up.</para>

        <para lang='en'>In the column <emphasis role="bold">Material type/VAT/Discount</emphasis>, define a discount and or select a material type. If there is a discount on this type of product by the supplier, the corresponding discount rate will be entered for the item ordered.</para>

        <para lang='en'>In the column <emphasis role="bold">Budget</emphasis>, you can link the item ordered to your budgetar.</para>

        <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Warning</emphasis> if your acquisitions budget parameter is set to 1, you must link the item ordered to a budget. For more information, consulter the <emphasis>PMB Administrator's Guide, chapter Tools,section Parameters</emphasis>.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="acquis_achats_commandes_etat">
        <title lang='en'>Saving, Deleting or Changing the status of an order</title>

        <para lang='en'>To save your order, click on the button <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis> at bottom of screen for adding or modifying an order.</para>

        <para lang='en'>to delete an order, click on the button <emphasis role="bold">Delete</emphasis> at bottom right of screen as soon as the order is displayed in edit mode.</para>

        <para lang='en'>To confirm an order, click on the button <emphasis role="bold">Validate</emphasis>.</para>
        
        <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">Warning</emphasis> Once an order is validated, you will not be able to modify it</para>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>Once confirmed, this order cannot be modified or deleted</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/acquisition-alerte-validation-commande.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para lang='en'>To indicate reception of an order and prepare a delivery note, click on the button <emphasis role="bold">Received</emphasis> on a confirmed order.</para>

        <para lang='en'>To indicate the invoicing of an order, click on the button <emphasis role="bold">Invoicing </emphasis>on a confirmed order.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="acquis_achats_livraisons">
      <title lang='en'>Deliveries</title>

      <para lang='en'>To create a delivery note, display a confirmed order in edit mode and click on the button <emphasis role="bold">Received</emphasis>.</para>

      <para lang='en'>To indicate reception of an order, display the order in edit mode, then click on <emphasis role="bold">Received</emphasis>.</para>

      <para lang='en'>By clicking on Received, you create a new delivery note. You can look for a given code in the list. This allows you subsequently to manually modify the quantity received. Similarly you can check the checkbox "<emphasis role="bold">auto</emphasis>". This allows you to increase the quantity received for an order automatically.</para>

      <figure>
        <title lang='en'>Acquisitions &gt; Deliveries</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/acquisition-livraison2.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para lang='en'>For example, if you have ordered three copies of <emphasis>Earth from the Air</emphasis> by Yann Arthus-Bertrand, by checking the checkbox, you would be able to read the three barcodes as and when the copies are received. Next click on  <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis> to create a delivery note.</para>

      <figure>
        <title lang='en'>Acquisitions &gt; Deliveries</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/acquisition-livraison-recue.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para lang='en'>To print a delivery note, click on the <emphasis>Print</emphasis> icon from the list of deliveries.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="acquis_achats_factures">
      <title lang='en'>Invoices</title>

      <para lang='en'>To record an invoice, display a confirmed order in edit mode and click on the button <emphasis role="bold">Invoicing</emphasis>.</para>

      <figure>
        <title lang='en'>Acquisitions &gt; Orders, Displaying an order in edit mode for invoicing</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/acquisition-livraison-a-facturer.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para lang='en'>You can recall a code from the list. This allows you subsequently to manually modify the number of items invoiced.</para>

      <para lang='en'>You can process the settlement of an invoice in edit mode by clicking on <emphasis role="bold">Pay</emphasis>. Warning, once an invoice has been settled, it cannot be deleted or modified.</para>

      <para lang='en'>You can also print the follow-up of an invoice by clicking on the <emphasis>Print</emphasis> icon from the list of invoices.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="acquis_achats_fournisseurs">
      <title lang='en'>Suppliers</title>

      <para lang='en'>You need to create one supplier at least to be able to create orders.</para>

      <para lang='en'>To create a supplier, click on  <emphasis role="bold">Add supplier</emphasis>. You can define a name or corporate name, a customer account number as well as a main address and additional addresses (Add address). You can define <emphasis       role="bold">notes</emphasis>, a <emphasis role="bold">SIRET</emphasis>, an <emphasis role="bold">RCS</emphasis>, a code <emphasis role="bold">NAF</emphasis>, a <emphasis       role="bold">TVA</emphasis> account number, a <emphasis role="bold">web site</emphasis>.</para>

      <para lang='en'>For a supplier, you can also define <emphasis role="bold">Terms of purchase</emphasis>.</para>

      <para lang='en'>The <emphasis role="bold">terms of purchase</emphasis> are made up of :</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>payment conditions : you can choose from the drop down list a <emphasis>method of payment</emphasis> via <emphasis>Administration &gt; Acquisitions</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>discounts by material type : you can define a discount for every one  material type defined via <emphasis>Administration &gt; Acquisitions</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="acquis_achats_devis">
      <title lang='en'>Quotations</title>

      <para lang='en'>To create a quotation request, click on <emphasis role="bold">New quotation</emphasis>.</para>

      <para lang='en'>A quotation request will enable you to find out with your supplier the availability and price of documents you wish to purchase.</para>

      <para lang='en'>Adding a new entry to a quotation request is similar to that of an order form. For more information, consult <xref linkend="acquis_achats_commandes_lignes" />.</para>

      <para lang='en'>You can use a <emphasis role="bold">confirmed quotation request</emphasis>  to place an order.</para>

      <para lang='en'>Similarly you can use the drop down list to change the status of a quotation request : <emphasis role="bold">current</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">received</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">filed</emphasis>.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="acquis_sugg">
    <title lang='en'>Suggestions</title>

    <sect2 id="acquis_sugg_atraiter">
      <title lang='en'>To process</title>

      <para lang='en'>Vous pouvez consulter les différentes suggestions pour les traiter
      ou créer une nouvelle suggestion en cliquant sur le bouton
      <emphasis>Créer une suggestion</emphasis>.</para>

      <sect3 id="acquis_sugg_rechercher">
        <title lang='en'>Rechercher et traiter une suggestion</title>

        <para lang='en'>Vous pouvez fusionner des transactions, les imprimer.</para>

        <para lang='en'>Pour les transactions en cours, vous pouvez</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>Imprimer</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>Fusionner</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>Valider</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>Rejeter</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>Supprimer</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para lang='en'>Pour les transactions rejetées ou abandonnées, vous
        pouvez</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>Imprimer</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>Archiver</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para lang='en'>Pour les transactions validées, vous pouvez</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>Imprimer</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>Fusionner</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>Confirmer</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>Abandonner</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para lang='en'>Pour les transactions confirmées, vous pouvez</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>Imprimer</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>Commander</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="acquis_sugg_create">
        <title lang='en'>Créer une suggestion</title>

        <figure>
          <title lang='en'>Acquisitions &gt; Suggestion : à traiter, Création d'une
          suggestion</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/creation-suggestion.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para lang='en'>L'écran de création d'une suggestion est divisée en deux
        partie.</para>

        <para lang='en'>Les informations en haut de l'écran sont non modifiables et
        indiquent :</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>la date de création</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>le login de l'utilisateur qui crée la suggestion</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>une pondération en fonction du type d'utilisateur. La
            pondération de la suggestion est fonction du paramètre
            <emphasis>Acquisitions</emphasis> <emphasis>poids_sugg</emphasis>.
            Pour plus d'informations, consulter le <emphasis>Guide de
            l'administrateur PMB, chapitre Outils, section
            Paramètres</emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>un état. Pour plus d'informations, consulter plus loin <xref
            linkend="acquis_sugg_etats" />.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para lang='en'>Dans le formulaire de création de suggestion, vous pouvez
        définir :</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>un titre</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>un éditeur</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>un auteur</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>un ISBN</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>un prix</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>une URL associée</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang='en'>des commentaires</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para lang='en'>Vous devez renseigner au moins un titre ainsi qu'un auteur ou un
        titre ainsi qu'un éditeur. Les autres champs sont facultatifs.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="acquis_sugg_etats">
      <title lang='en'>Liste des états des suggestions</title>

      <para lang='en'>Voici la liste des états que peut prendre une suggestion, avec la
      liste des étapes ayant amené la suggestion à cette étape : </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'><emphasis role="bold">en cours</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>en cours &gt; <emphasis role="bold">validé</emphasis> : la
          suggestion est valide. Les informations de la suggestion transmise
          sont suffisantes pour pouvoir envisager une recherche du document
          demandé. A cette étape, on ne prend pas en compte le fait d'être
          d'accord ou non avec la suggestion, il s'agit juste d'un contrôle de
          validité.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>en cours &gt; <emphasis role="bold">rejeté</emphasis> :
          suggestion invalide ou trop incomplète pour réaliser la moindre
          recherche</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>en cours &gt; validé &gt; <emphasis
          role="bold">confirmé</emphasis> : la suggestion valide est retenue
          pour une prochaine commande</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>en cours &gt; validé &gt; <emphasis
          role="bold">abandonné</emphasis> : la suggestion valide ne
          correspond pas aux critères de choix ou au budget par exemple. La
          suggestion ne sera pas commandée.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>en cours &gt; validé &gt; confirmé &gt; <emphasis
          role="bold">commandé</emphasis> : la suggestion valide a été retenue
          puis commandée</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para lang='en'>en cours &gt; validé &gt; confirmé &gt; commandé &gt;
          <emphasis role="bold">reçu</emphasis> : la suggestion commandée est
          reçue</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>