<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title>Subjects</title>

  <para>The PMB subject index corresponds to a subject arrangement of the
  library collection. The subjects are arranged to form a herarchically
  structured thesaurus.</para>

  <para>The subject index can be displayed or not on the OPAC home page
  depending on your library's requirements, and the subjects that you can
  browse in PMB correspond to choices made by your library.</para>

  <section id="opac_categ_browser">
    <title>Browsing the subject index</title>

    <figure>
      <title>The display of subjects on the OPAC home page</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/images/categs_home.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The subject index on the OPAC enables you to browse the virtual
    shelves of a library like you would be doing on Yahoo.</para>

    <para>Depending on your library settings, the OPAC home page displays a
    subject browser. Under each of the main subject headings (here, Art and
    Culture, Social sciences, for example), are listed the first sub-headings.
    </para>

    <para>A subject heading may contain one or more sub-headings, or none.
    Under this subject may fall one or more works of the library, or none. A
    subject heading may also contain references: "see" references directing
    the user to another subject, or "see also" references suggesting the
    reader to look also under another subject.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Relative subject index</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/images/categ_detail.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Quick search by subject</title>

    <para>Enter one or more keywords, tick Subjects to confine the search to
    Subjects only, and then click on Search to validate.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Quick search by subject</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/images/categs_search_1.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <figure>
      <title>Search result for quick search</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/images/categs_search_2.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Search by terms under subject</title>

    <para>Search by terms is useful for browsing and surfing from one subject
    to another. The central interface is divided in two areas to allow for
    subject-to-subject browsing.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Search by terms under subject</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/images/categs_terms.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>For more details, see <xref linkend="opac_search_terms" /></para>
  </section>
</chapter>