<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title lang='en'>Mac OS X, FreeBSD, other UNIX systems</title>

  <sect1>
    <title lang='en'>FreeBSD</title>

    <para lang='en'>We have no feedback as yet from anyone using a FreeBSD system. Do
    not hesitate to contact us and pass on any information.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title lang='en'>Unix</title>

    <para lang='en'>We have no feedback from anyone using a Unix system (other than
    Linux). Do not hesitate to contact us and pass on any information.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title lang='en'>Mac OS X</title>

    <para lang='en'>Linux is not the only open source operating system of the Unix
    family. Mac OS X, the latest system from Apple, is partially based on
    Unix.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title lang='en'>Using MAMP</title>

      <para lang='en'>MAMP is an Apache 2, PHP, MySQL package available at <ulink
      url="???"><ulink url="???"><ulink
      url="???">www.mamp.info</ulink></ulink></ulink>.</para>

      <para lang='en'>To install PMB on MAMP, unzip the PMB archive into
      Applications/MAMP/htdocs.</para>

      <para lang='en'>When installing the database, specify :</para>

      <para lang='en'>user mysql : root</para>

      <para lang='en'>password : root</para>

      <para lang='en'>server : 127.0.0.1:8889</para>

      <para lang='en'>database : bibli</para>

      <para lang='en'>For the rest, consult the general information on
      installation.</para>

      <para lang='en'>Note : MAMP is distributed with the YAZ extension (z39.50) for Mac
      activated in PHP4. Cataloguing with z39.50 is immediately available for
      PMB users on MAMP, no further configuration needed.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title lang='en'>Using the Apache and PHP distribution supplied with Mac OS
      X</title>

      <para lang='en'>Go to System Preferences, then Share, and activate Web sharing.
      The files found in /Library/Webserver/Documents correspond to files
      accessible by PMB : extract the PMB archive downloaded on www.sigb.net
      in this directory.</para>

      <para lang='en'>MySQL is not supplied with Mac OS X. You will find a MySQL version
      at www.mysql.com.</para>

      <para lang='en'>Once the PMB files have been extracted, you need to configure the
      PMB database. To do this, start your browser, Safari for example, and go
      to the address http://localhost/pmb/tables/install.php.</para>

      <para lang='en'>PMB is accessible from now on at http://localhost/pmb.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title lang='en'>Activating YAZ on Mac OS X</title>

      <para lang='en'>You can download the file yaz.so available at <ulink
      url="???">http://www.sigb.net/mac</ulink> and install it in the PHP
      directory of your machine. In your <citetitle>php.ini</citetitle>, in
      the section extensions, add the line extension=yaz.so and restart your
      Apache server to activate it. To do this, go to System Preferences,
      Share; deactivate Web sharing and activate it once again.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>