<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter lang="fr">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para></para>

  <sect1 id="introduction_sujetpmb">
    <title>About PMB</title>

    <para>PMB is a completely free ILS (Integrated Library management System).
    The domain of software for libraries is almost exclusively occupied by
    proprietary products. We are some librarians, users and developers
    deploring this state of affairs.</para>

    <para>PMB is based on web technology. This is what we sometimes call a
    'web-app'. PMB requires an HTTP server (such as Apache, but this is not an
    obligation), the MySQL database and the PHP language.</para>

    <para>The main functions of PMB are :</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Support for the UNIMARC format</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Authorities management (authors, publishers, series,
        subjects...)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Management of loans, holds, borrowers...</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A user-friendly configuration</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The ability to import full bibliographic records</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A user-friendly OPAC integrating a browser</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Loans management with a module designed to serve even the very
        small establishments</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Serials management</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Simple administration procedures that can be handled easily even
        by the library staff...</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>More details can be found at www.sigb.net</para>

    <para>There you will also find an online demo version, the PMB users Web
    page, and the latest versions of the Installation Guide, the User Guide,
    and the Administrator Guide.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="introduction_infos">
    <title>Where to find information about PMB</title>

    <para>At the PMB website: www.sigb.net</para>

    <para>At the users' forum: www.sigb.net/communaute</para>

    <para>Via the users' mailing lists : pmb.user@sigb.net (free subscription,
    just send an email subject SUBSCRIBE to pmb.user_request@sigb.net)</para>

    <para>Via the mailing lists for translators, developers, for Unicode
    support (non European alphabets). For more information on these lists, go
    to <ulink url="http://www.sibg.net">www.sigb.net</ulink></para>

    <para>This documentation is viewable online at www.sigb.net/doc, the HTML
    version may be downloaded freely, it can be integrated within PMB to
    become a contextual help.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="introduction_references">
    <title>References</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Authors</emphasis></para>

    <para>Gautier MICHELIN, Eric ROBERT, Florent TETART and, as the case may
    be, the writers of certain sections of this documentation.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Installation on the various
    platforms</emphasis></para>

    <para>The names of the various authors are mentioned in their
    contributions headings.</para>

    <para>PMB is rights free, its source code is the collective work of many
    developers, of whom the authors of this guide. Thank you all.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="introduction_cvs">
    <title>CVS</title>

    <para>CVS stands for Concurrent Versions System. It is a tool for
    programmers for the management of source code updates.</para>

    <para>PMB uses a CVS. The CVS is accessible to developers. Do not hesitate
    to contact us if you wish to help with the development of PMB or to
    participate in the write-up of the documentation.</para>

    <para>For more information, contact the developers of
    PMB<emphasis>.</emphasis></para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>