<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>PMB is a highly configurable application. Parameters linked to readers, statistical processes, operations of the Z39.50 client, all can be customized.</para>

  <para>Moreover, the administration tab allows multiple database-related functions, like optimizing the database tables, or routine PMB operations like user management (librarians).</para>

  <para>The administration tab, in addition to its importance, has more screens than any other PMB tab. For this reason, we have decided to introduce this guide separately to facilitate the update of the information presented here.</para>

  <sect1>
    <title>Credits</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Authors</emphasis></para>

    <para>Gautier MICHELIN, Eric ROBERT, Florent TETART</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Contributions</emphasis></para>

    <para>PMB development team.</para>

    <para>Former PMB developers: François Lemarchand, Jesir Vargas, Christophe Bliard, ...</para>

    <para>This administrator's guide corresponds to PMB version 2.1</para>

    <para>Version number on the cover page.</para></sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>About PMB</title>

    <para>PMB is a free integrated library management software. For more information, refer to <ulink url="http://www.sigb.net">http://www.sigb.net</ulink> .</para></sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Organization of the Administration Tab </title>

    <figure>
      <title>Administration Tab</title>

      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/admin.gif"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure>

    <para>The administration tab has a menu located on the left hand side of the screen, and within each of the various sub-menus there is a links bar located on top on the screen.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Links bar on top of the screen</title>

      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/lien_haut.gif"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure>

    <para>A screen capture of the side menu is represented below. This document is organized in chapters corresponding to some extent to every option of this menu.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Side Menu</title>

      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/admin_menu.gif"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure></sect1></chapter>