<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="admin_expl">
  <title>Copies</title>

  <para><emphasis>Administration</emphasis> &gt; <emphasis>Copies</emphasis>
  allows you to customize the cataloguing of copies of works in your library.
  You can customize media type, statistical code, section, status, location,
  owner, and finally add customizable fields to your copies.</para>

  <sect1 id="admin_expl_typdoc">
    <title>Media types</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Media types</emphasis> allows configuration of
    the various types of documents and for each one of them the loan period in
    days.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Warning</emphasis>, we are talking here of
    types of documents that will be displayed for the copy and not for the
    bibliographical record. They are defined here to supplement or provide
    details about the type of document defined for the work. In PMB the medium
    type for works is normalized in UNIMARC.</para>

    <para>Type of document is also used to define <emphasis role="">Loan
    period</emphasis> or <emphasis role="">Duration of hold</emphasis> for an
    item.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Warning</emphasis> If advanced loans quotas
    are enabled (parameter type <emphasis>pmb</emphasis>, sub-type
    <emphasis>advanced-quotas</emphasis> set to 1), the columns Loan period
    and Duration of hold display <emphasis role=""> See quotas</emphasis>. For
    more information, refer to <xref linkend="admin_quotas" /> and <xref
    linkend="admin_outils_parametres" />.</para>

    <para>Both columns <emphasis role="">Coding owners</emphasis> and
    <emphasis role="">Import coding</emphasis> correspond to the management of
    data gathered while importing UNIMARC copies, they are used to establish
    the link with the type of document already defined. For more information,
    refer to the chapter <emphasis>Definitions</emphasis>.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Copies &gt; type of document</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_cat_doctypes.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="admin_expl_codstat">
    <title>Statistical codes</title>

    <para>The statistical code is used for loan statistics and for the library
    holdings.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Copies &gt; Statistical codes</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_cat_codstat.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Both columns <emphasis role="">Coding owners</emphasis> and
    <emphasis role="">Import coding</emphasis> correspond to the management of
    data gathered while importing UNIMARC copies, they are used to establish
    the link with the type of document already defined. For more information,
    refer to the chapter <emphasis>Definitions</emphasis>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="admin_expl_section">
    <title>Sections</title>

    <para>Section is the division of the library to which the document belongs
    (adult, youth, music ...). This code is taken into account for the
    calculation of statistics, for example.</para>

    <para>Section might also correspond to a geographical area of the library,
    it can be as large as a room or as small as a shelf.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Copies &gt; Sections</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_cat_sections.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Both columns <emphasis role="">Coding owners</emphasis> and
    <emphasis role="">Import coding</emphasis> correspond to the management of
    data gathered while importing UNIMARC copies, they are used to establish a
    link with a section already defined. See the chapter <xref
    linkend="definitions" /> for more information.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="admin_expl_statut">
    <title>Status</title>

    <para>Status is used to specify whether the document can be loaned or
    not.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Copies &gt; Status</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_cat_status.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Status generally deals with a physical state (damaged, good, lost)
    or the whereabouts of the book between ordering and loan to readers (on
    order, in acquisition, in cataloguing, in repairs ...).</para>

    <para>Both columns <emphasis role="">Coding owners</emphasis> and
    <emphasis role="">Import coding</emphasis> correspond to the management of
    data gathered while importing UNIMARC copies, they are used to establish a
    link with a status already defined. For more information, refer to the
    chapter <emphasis>Definitions</emphasis>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="admin_expl_location">
    <title>Locations</title>

    <para>Location can be used to link the document with a specific
    geographical location (example: in reserve).</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Copies &gt; Location</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_cat_loc.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>This location notion is very important for multi-site libraries. It
    can also be very useful for specialized documentation centres: research
    laboratory or company where books can be loaned for a rather long period.
    These have been taken off the shelves and have been transferred to the
    design department or the study of a scientist. In this case, PMB can be
    used to define a location <emphasis>Design department</emphasis> and a
    corresponding status <emphasis>Reference work</emphasis>, for which the
    loan would obviously be impossible because the copy is absent from the
    shelves. This solution allows for the tracing of books required outside of
    the library without necessitating a loan for a period left
    undetermined.</para>

    <para>Both columns <emphasis role="">Coding owners</emphasis> and
    <emphasis role="">Import coding</emphasis> correspond to the management of
    data gathered while importing UNIMARC copies, they are used to establish a
    link with the type of document already defined. For more information,
    refer to the chapter <emphasis>Definitions</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>You can define different parameters for each location. For example,
    these parameters can be used for overdue letters or the library address.
    Each time the library address is required, PMB looks for the corresponding
    value in location.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="admin_expl_lenders">
    <title>Owners</title>

    <para>You will find here the list of owners of copies managed in the
    catalogue. You can mention here the collection made available to you by
    your Departmental Lending Library, a collection bequeathed to the library,
    a donation that you wish to identify ...</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Copies &gt; owners</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_expl_propr.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="admin_expl_perso">
    <title>Customizable data</title>

    <para>These correspond to your own library information regarding copies.
    It allows you to specify your management data: source of donation or
    financing for the acquisition, ...</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Copies &gt; Customizable data</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_expl_perso.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Example. Let's add a field entitled <emphasis>Type of book
    cover</emphasis> that will enable us to specify the type of binding of a
    book. Bindings can be of 3 types: soft, hardback, paperback. Since not all
    copies correspond to books, we will add another choice: Not
    Applicable.</para>

    <para>Click on <emphasis>New field</emphasis> <graphic
    fileref="images/nouveau_champ.gif" /></para>

    <para>The following screen is displayed:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Copies &gt; Customizable data, New field</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_expl_nouveau_champ.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>For name of field, enter <emphasis>cover</emphasis> (do not use
    accents, spaces or punctuation marks in the name for a field), for title
    to display, enter <emphasis>cover</emphasis> (you can also use a name with
    spaces but only for display purposes, for example <emphasis>Type of
    cover</emphasis>).</para>

    <para>For type of entry choose <emphasis>List box</emphasis>. Then click
    on <emphasis>Options</emphasis>.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Options for the List box type</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/chp_perso_options_liste.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Click on <emphasis>Add</emphasis> 4 times to define 4 different
    choices: paperback, soft, hardback, Not Applicable. The stored values in
    the database are paperback, soft, hardback and nocover. You will then
    obtain the result displayed above. Now click on <emphasis>Save</emphasis>
    to close the popup window, and finally on <emphasis>Save</emphasis> to add
    your parameter.</para>

    <para>You can now use your new customized field for any input or
    modification of a copy. For more information on the creation of a copy,
    refer to the <emphasis>PMB User's Guide</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>In Cataloguing &gt; record &gt; new record, after creating a new
    record, you can add a copy. You will then see your new customized
    field.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Editing a copy, the customized field Type of cover has been
      added</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/chp_perso_expl.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <sect2>
      <title>Types of input for customizable fields</title>

      <para>Other types of input exist for a customizable field than the list
      box type.</para>

      <para>There are five types of customizable fields:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>text</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>list box</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>list box from a query</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>date selection</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>note zone</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Each one of these types has 5 different options. Click on
      <emphasis>Options </emphasis>to specify the parameters for these
      fields.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Text type</title>

        <figure>
          <title>Options for the text type</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/chp_perso_options_texte.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>For a text type you can specify its screen size. You can also
        specify the maximum number of letters to enter (if larger that the
        specified size on screen, you will still be able to enter even when
        you reach the end of the input box).</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>List box type</title>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Warning</emphasis> you cannot create
        options for the choices until the field has been recorded. From the
        screen add a parameter, record the customizable field. Then click on
        its name to modify it and specify options.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Options for the List box type</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/chp_perso_options_liste.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>For a list box you can specify:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>if it is a multiple choice list (to select multiple choices
            in a list with your internet browser, you need to click on the
            choices while holding down the control key.)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the default value. When no choice is made, this is the value
            that will be displayed.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>a list of options, This list includes a <emphasis
            role="bold">label</emphasis>: the text that will be displayed on
            screen; a <emphasis role="bold">value</emphasis>: the value that
            will be stored in PMB (accents, spaces, punctuation marks ... are
            not allowed). A sort order for the various options can be
            specified.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>With the action buttons you can:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>add an extra choice to the list</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>delete the choices you have ticked on the checkbox at the
            beginning of each corresponding line</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>record your changes</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>List box from a query type</title>

        <figure>
          <title>Options for a List box from a query type</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/chp_perso_options_liste_req.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>For a List box from a query you can specify:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>if it is a multiple choice list (to select multiple choices
            in a list with you internet browser, you need to click on the
            choices while holding down the control key.)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the default value. When no choice is made, this is the value
            that will be displayed</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>a query that will display the options list.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>With the action buttons you can:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>test your query. When you click on the button, the choices
            returned by the query are displayed below the button. This will
            enable you to check the validity of your query.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>record your changes</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Date type</title>

        <figure>
          <title>Options for the Date type</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/chp_perso_options_date.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>There are no particular options for customizable fields of date
        type. Clicking on the Options button will only display the message
        above.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Comment zone type</title>

        <figure>
          <title>Options for the Comment zone type</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/chp_perso_options_comm.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Fields of the type Comment zone work the same way as text
        fields. In addition, you can specify a number of lines for the comment
        field.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Data types, visible in OPAC, mandatory</title>

      <para>Five types of data can be stored in the PMB database: text, large
      text, integer, date, decimal number.</para>

      <para><emphasis>Visible in OPAC</emphasis> allows to choose if this
      field will be visible to readers. In this way you can add fields
      reserved for the library personnel: for example, the name of the person
      who created the record, ...</para>

      <para><emphasis>Mandatory</emphasis> specifies that the field must be
      filled in. If the field is not filled in during input or editing of an
      item, an error message is displayed.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Warning for a blank mandatory field</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/alerte_champs.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>