<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title>Z39.50</title>

  <para>If the Z39.50 search option is enabled, it will be visible from the
  cataloguing tab. To enable Z39.50 search, the parameter Z3950.accessible
  must be set to 1. For more details on customizing PMB, see <xref
  linkend="admin_outils_parametres" />.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Warning : </emphasis>z39.50 search implies
  installing and enabling the PHP module YAZ on your web server. For more
  details, please read the PMB installation guide.</para>

  <para>Z29.50 search allows you to import bibliographic data from a
  bibliographic records server like the Library of Congress. Provided the
  Library of Congress server is accessible from your computer connected to
  Internet, you will enjoy the benefits of an automated book cataloging system
  for every publication falling under legal deposit in the United
  States.</para>

  <para>All you need then is to enter one or more subjects (thesaurus terms),
  eventually some keywords and your own notes, and finally create one or more
  copies depending on your holdings.</para>

  <para>The Z39.50 search allows you to save considerable cataloguing time.
  You will find the z39.50 search in the Cataloguing side menu, for more
  details, please read the PMB user's guide, chapter Cataloguing.</para>

  <figure>
    <title>z39.50</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../../pmb2.1/doc/documentation/en_UK/html-admin/images/admin_z39_home.gif" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect1>
    <title>Servers</title>

    <para>Z39.50 &gt; Servers lists of all Z39.50 servers available in search
    mode. You can add here a new server or update an existing one.</para>

    <para>For each server you will need different parameters like the type of
    data returned, a userid and a password, etc. Contact the Z39.50 server
    administrator directly to obtain this profile. You can also search
    "profile Z39.50" on Google.</para>

    <para>If you are a member of an RLS (regional library service) network,
    ask your RLS administrator for his Z39.50 server profile, if
    necessary.</para>

    <para>The PMB distribution already contains a number of parameters of
    servers of French-speaking establishments and the Library of Congress,
    United States.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Z39.50 &gt; Servers &gt; Edit server</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../../pmb2.1/doc/documentation/en_UK/html-admin/images/admin_z39.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>You will need the following parameters to customize your Z39.50
    servers :</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Server name : the name that will be displayed on the screen. You
        may define it.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Base : this information is part of the Z39.50 server
        profile.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Usage : CATALOG (cataloguing). PMB allows only Z39.50 usage for
        cataloging.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>URL : server address. This information is part of the Z39.50
        server profile.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Port number : this information is part of the Z39.50 server
        profile.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Format : this information is part of the Z39.50 server
        profile.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Userid and password : ID used to connect to the server. This
        information is part of the Z39.50 server profile.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Finally, the Z39.50 server profile defines various attributes
    accessible by clicking on the Attribute button. They are the various
    search criteria of the Z39.50 server.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Z39.50 &gt; Z39.50 search attributes management</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../../pmb2.1/doc/documentation/en_UK/html-admin/images/Z39_attributs.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Each attribute is made up of a label and a numerical server
    attribute.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>