<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- 
+==========================================================================+
| PMB                                                                      |
+==========================================================================+
| (c) 2002-2004 PMB Services / www.sigb.net pmb@sigb.net et contributeurs  |
| (voir www.sigb.net)                                                      |
| creator : Gautier MICHELIN                                               |
| modified : ...                                                           |
+==========================================================================+
-->
<chapter>
  <title>Z39.50</title>

  <para>If Z39.50 search option is enabled, it's visible from the cataloging
  tab. To enable the Z39.50 search, the parameter Z3950.accessible must be set
  to 1. For more details on the PMB customization, see <xref
  linkend="admin_outils_parametres" />.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Caution : </emphasis>z39.50 search implies
  installing and enabling the PHP module YAZ on your web server. For more
  details, please read the PMB installation guide.</para>

  <para>Z29.50 search allows you to import bibliographic data from a notice
  server like the one of the British Library. Provided that the British
  Library server is accessible from you computer connected to Internet, you
  will benefit of an automated book cataloging for every book that has been
  concerned by a legal deposit to the British Library.</para>

  <para>You just need then to set one or more categories (thesaurus),
  eventually some keywords and your own notes, and finally create one or more
  items corresponding to your material situation.</para>

  <para>The Z39.50 search allows you to greatly decrease the cataloging time.
  You will find it from the Cataloging tab, for more details, please read the
  PMB user's guide, chapter Cataloging.</para>

  <figure>
    <title>z39.50</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/admin_z39_home.gif" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect1>
    <title>Servers</title>

    <para>Z39.50 &gt; Servers gives you a list of all Z39.50 servers available
    in search mode. You can add here a new server or update an existing
    one.</para>

    <para>For each server, you will need some parameters like the type of data
    returned, a userid and a password, etc. Contact directly the Z39.50 server
    administrator to get this profile. You can also search Google with the
    following search criteria "profile Z39.50" .</para>

    <para>If you are a member of a RLS (regional library service) network,
    ask, if necessary, the RLS administrator his Z39.50 server profile.</para>

    <para>PMB is provided with several server parameters corresponding to
    French-speaking needs and the American Library of Congress.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Z39.50 &gt; Servers &gt; Modify the server</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_z39.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The customization of Z39.50 parameters is composed of various
    elements :</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Server name : this is the name that will be displayed on the
        screen. You may define it.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Base : this information is part of the Z39.50 server
        profile.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Usage : CATALOG (cataloguing). PMB allows only Z39.50 usage for
        cataloging.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>URL : server address. This information is part of the Z39.50
        server profile.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Port number : this information is part of the Z39.50 server
        profile.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Format : Information this information is part of the Z39.50
        server profile.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Userid and password : ID used to connect to the server. Those
        informations are part of the Z39.50 server profile.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Finally, the Z3905 server profile defines various attributes
    accessibles by clicking on the Attribute button. Those are the various
    search criterias of the Z39.50 server.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Z39.50 &gt; Z39.50 search attributes management</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/Z39_attributs.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Each attribute is composed of a label and a numeric server
    attribute.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>