<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="admin_notices">
  <title>Bibliographical Notes</title>

  <para>Most of the data defining a bibliographical note are standardized. However PMB allows editing of a table originating from a bibliographical note. You can also add customizable fields.</para>

  <sect1 id="admin_notices_orinot">
    <title>Sources</title>

    <para>This represents the source of a bibliographical note. PMB imports notes mainly via z39.50 or through UNIMARC import. However these bibliographical notes are copyrighted. The National French Library Library bibliographical notes can be used freely, however it might not necessarily be the same for a few professionals in this domain. Indeed, the company Electre publishes a CD-Rom of bibliographical notes, updated with the latest publications. This CD-Rom is not free, and each one of its bibliographical notes are copyrighted.</para>

    <para>Since version 1.3, PMB manages the source of bibliographical notes.</para>

    <para>The administrative function for the sources of the notes allows to predefine sources for the notes. It also allows editing of the imported sources of bibliographical notes.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Notes &gt; Notes sources</title>

      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/admin_cat_notices.gif"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure></sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Status</title>

    <para>The status of a bibliographical note allows to distinguish between treatment and cataloguing for notes, as well as the display in OPAC.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Notes &gt; Status</title>

      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/admin_notices_statut.gif"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure>

    <para>The notes status table shows various information:</para>

    <itemizedlist><listitem><para>a display class (1 to 9), corresponds to a color rectangle on the left of the table. This marker quickly identifies the status of the note, for example during a search in the cataloguing tab.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>being visible or not during management. This will allow management of a &quot;reservoir of notes&quot;, for example by saving destroyed notes with a &quot;destroy&quot; status.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>for OPAC, </para>

        <itemizedlist><listitem><para>potential label (e.g. being ordered)</para></listitem>

          <listitem><para>Notes visibility</para></listitem>

          <listitem><para>copies display</para></listitem>

          <listitem><para>digital copies display</para></listitem></itemizedlist></listitem></itemizedlist>

    <para>To add a new status for a bibliographical note, click on the appropriate button at the bottom of the screen.</para>

    <para>To modify a the status of a note, click on the corresponding line in the table,</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Notes &gt; Status, modify the status</title>

      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/admin_notices_statut2.gif"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure>

    <para>From the modification screen, you can also restrict the display of notes, copies, digital copies, to subscribers only (readers and borrowers with a login and password). If restrictions apply, the reader will have to be identified in order to remove these restrictions.</para></sect1>

  <sect1 id="admin_notices_perso">
    <title>Customizable data</title>

    <para>This is about the customizable fields of a bibliographical note. These customizable fields allow specification of information about your own library or documentation center in bibliographical notes: source of the acquisition idea, commentary of a reading committee, targeted readers...</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Notes &gt; Customizable data</title>

      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/admin_cat_perso_notice.gif"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure>

    <figure>
      <title></title>

      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="???"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure>

    <para>Operations on customizable fields are identical to the ones for copies. For more information, refer to <xref linkend="admin_expl_perso"/>.</para></sect1></chapter>
