<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="admin_gestion_financiere">
  <title>Financial management</title>

  <para>The module financial management of membership enables you to monitor
  financial transactions relating to the library's readership. These may be of
  different types :</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>membership fees</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>fines on overdue items</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>loans fees relating to one or more types of documents (for
      example, DVD), either as a whole, or based on the loan period...</para>

      <para><figure>
          <title>Figure 9.1. Administration, Financial management</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../../../../../../../pmb/doc/documentation/en_UK/html-admin/images/admin_fin_home.gif" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>From this screen you can manage fines and suspension of
      loans.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <sect1>
    <title>Basic notions</title>

    <para>How the financial management module in PMB functions rests on a
    number of factors of which you need a very good understanding to be able
    to use the module.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Types of readers accounts</title>

      <para>There are three types of accounts for each reader :</para>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A membership account : in which shall be recorded financial
            transactions relating to membership</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A loans account : in which shall be recorded the dues
            regarding the loan of certain types of documents (DVD for
            example)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A fines account : in which shall be recorded the fines
            relating to overdue items as well as the settlement of
            fines.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>The Library account</title>

      <para>Similarly the library possesses an account that will enable it to
      manage in some cases the rebates on the readers accounts. La
      bibliothèque possède également un compte, qui permettra de gérer dans
      certains cas les remises accordées sur les comptes lecteurs. This
      account can never be in credit. It is just a debit account listing
      rebates. On no account shall it show a surplus. Ce compte ne peut jamais
      être positif. Il s'agit uniquement d'un compte de débit listant des
      remises. En aucun il ne pourra être bénéficiaire.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Managing membership</title>

    <para></para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Adding a membership type</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Managing tariffs of loans</title>

    <para></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Managing fines</title>

    <para></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Managing fines : overdue items</title>

    <para></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Suspension of loans</title>

    <para></para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>