<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="admin_users">
  <title>Users</title>

  <para>In PMB, the <emphasis>user</emphasis> denomination refers to the
  application users and not the library users, that is readers or borrowers.
  An user is for example : a library assistant at the issue counter, a
  librarian, a software administrator, ...</para>

  <sect1>
    <title>Managing users</title>

    <para>The PMB users managment section will allow to create users profiles.
    For each user account, a userid and a password is created. PMB need at
    least on administrator account (superuser). This account can't be reased
    from within PMB.</para>

    <para>If you have uploaded the operationnal test data set of PMB, you have
    moreover three additionnal accounts : librarian (user :
    <emphasis>bib</emphasis>, password : <emphasis>bib</emphasis>),
    cataloguing agent (<emphasis>cat</emphasis> ; <emphasis>cat</emphasis>)
    and lending agent (<emphasis>circ</emphasis>:
    <emphasis>circ</emphasis>)</para>

    <para>Access rights to the various part of the software depends on the
    tabs. According to the access right granted (open padlock) of not (closed
    padlock), the corresponding tab will be shown or not. Only one exception
    to this rule : the backup feature is not displayed as a tab.</para>

    <para>You can here change an user and change his password. This last
    feature is usefull when someone moves to another job, or when the password
    is lost. The user may freely change his password witthout asking the
    administrator to do it, by clicking on the user preferences (preferences
    link on the top right of the screen).</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Managing users</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_util_gestion.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The preferences of an user, accessible by clicking on the modify
    button, corresponds to the user preferences accessible from the
    <emphasis>edit your account</emphasis> link next to the
    <emphasis>logout</emphasis> link.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>