<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="admin_empr">
  <title>Readers</title>

  <para>In this part of the administration tab, you can define your personal
  options useful for managing readers.</para>

  <sect1 id="admin_empr_categ">
    <title>Categories</title>

    <para>Defining multiple reader categories enables you to compile
    statistics on how your library is being used. For more information on
    compiling statistics with PMB, refer to <emphasis>PMB User's
    Guide</emphasis>, Chapter <emphasis>Management</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>If you have activated advanced quotas management, categories will
    enable you to specify quotas: for example, a child can borrow 2 works, an
    adult 5 works at the same time. For more information on advanced quotas
    management, refer to chapter <xref linkend="admin_quotas" />.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Readers categories</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_lect_cat.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>In France, the maintenance of a readers' file in public libraries is
    limited to one year, when the file is declared (statement mandatory with
    the CNIL) as using the simplified procedure mode.</para>

    <para>For more information, refer to <ulink
    url="http://www.culture.gouv.fr/culture/mrt/bibliotheque/dll/informatique/c4.pdf">http://www.culture.gouv.fr/culture/mrt/bibliotheque/dll/informatique/c4.pdf</ulink>.</para>

    <para>If you wish to be exempted from this limit, you need only extend the
    membership period to 9,999 days, for example.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis> if you have enabled financial
    management for readers, you can define a membership rate per reader
    category, displayed here in the third column. For more information, refer
    to chapter <xref linkend="admin_gestion_financiere" />.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="admin_empr_codstat">
    <title>Statistical codes</title>

    <para>Statistical codes are useful for producing readers' profiles by
    crossing data.</para>

    <para>Several options are available:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>use it to differentiate readers by age-group when birthdate is
        not required (less than 18, 18-35, 36-65, over 65 years of age, for
        example);</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>use it to assess your library's geographical coverage (example
        below)...</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <figure>
      <title>Readers statistical codes</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_lect_stat.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="admin_empr_implec">
    <title>Readers Import</title>

    <para>Importing a readers' file allows you to retrieve data from another
    application or else from a file that you would have built up: laboratory
    members with a specialized documentation centre, a students' list from a
    school, import from an LDAP directory, etc...</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Readers import</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_lect_imp.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Using the readers import screen you can either import readers from a
    file or delete readers.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Importing readers</title>

      <para>Import is effected from a text file (usually TXT or CSV type
      files). Spreadsheet applications (OpenOffice, Excel, ...) can export
      files in CSV format.</para>

      <para>Click on Browse to select the file to import. Depending on your
      file format, select a field separator. Select also a readers category
      and a statistical code: this information cannot be imported
      directly.</para>

      <para>Click Next to continue.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Readers import</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/admin_lect_imp2.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The following screen displays the list of fields in the readers'
      table.</para>

      <para>In the left hand side column are the fields names of the database.
      Readers data will be entered in these fields.</para>

      <para>The center column shows the position of the field in the
      file.</para>

      <para>The right hand side column shows an example of the first line of
      the file, it can be very useful when you want to change the position
      within the file. Enter the positions in the center column, and don't
      forget to click on Update to update the changes.</para>

      <para>Here is an example of an import file:</para>

      <programlisting>"12527","Archambault","rue de... "12528","Baudin","rue de...</programlisting>

      <para>12527 is the first position, it represents the reader's barcode,
      the second position is the reader's name, the third his address,
      etc....</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Important </emphasis> fields shown in red
      cannot be modified by the user, they are automatically filled in.</para>

      <para>After filling up your corresponding table click on Next.</para>

      <para>The number of persons processed by the readers import is finally
      displayed.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Deleting readers</title>

      <para>You can delete readers by clicking on the Delete readers button.
      Then checkmark the expiry date(s) of readers to delete, for example,
      expiry dates going back to more than a year.</para>

      <para>Click Delete.</para>

      <para>The list of readers matching the criteria is displayed.</para>

      <para>You can then click on Delete All to remove the corresponding
      readers.</para>

      <para>The number of persons that have been deleted is displayed on
      screen. Those that could not be deleted, for example, because they have
      current loans, are displayed.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Importing readers, advanced</title>

      <para>Advanced solutions for importing readers are available.</para>

      <para>Imported readers will be placed into an existing category. If you
      wish to fine tune your imports you can use
      <emphasis>phpmyadmin</emphasis> or link your data in an application
      using MyODBC. For more information on phpmyadmin, refer to the web site
      <ulink url="http://www.phpmyadmin.net">phpmyadmin</ulink> or, for more
      information on the installation [in French] refer to <ulink
      url="http://www.allhtml.com/mysql/mysql582.php">http://www.allhtml.com/mysql/mysql582.php</ulink>.</para>

      <para>MyODBC is an ODBC application, it allows you to edit MySQL data
      within your database application, for example, you can copy and paste
      data from a spreadsheet. For more information, refer to www.mysql.com or
      perform a google search on MyODBC.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="admin_empr_parperso">
    <title>Customized parameters</title>

    <para>Customized parameters allow you to add additional data to readers'
    cards. You can thus specify such information as company,
    socio-professional category....</para>

    <para>You must give a name to your parameter (accents and punctuation are
    not accepted in a field name, but you can use them in the title
    display).</para>

    <para>You may opt to make entries mandatory under this parameter.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Readers - Customized parameters</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_lect_param.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Customizable parameters function in the same manner as customized
    fields for copies or records. For more information, refer to <xref
    linkend="admin_expl_perso" />.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>