<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="admin_quotas">
  <title>Quotas</title>

  <para>There are two ways of handling quotas in PMB. Advanced quota management
  is enabled if the parameter pmb.quotas_avances is set to 1 in the
  <emphasis>Administration &gt; Tools &gt; parameters</emphasis>.</para>

  <para>When a circulation quota is reached, an alert warns the staff at the
  issue counter giving her/him the option, as the case may be, to force the
  loan. For more details, read the <emphasis>PMB user guide</emphasis>,
  <emphasis>Cirulation</emphasis> chapter.</para>

  <sect1>
    <title>If Advanced Quota Management is not enabled</title>

    <para><graphic fileref="images/warning.gif" /></para>

    <para>If advanced quota management is not enabled, you will not see
    "quotas" in the menu.</para>

    <para>In this case, only the loan period and the hold duration per media
    type can be set. For more details, see <xref
    linkend="admin_expl_typdoc" />.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Quotas : duration, quantity and types</title>

    <para>In PMB, there is two types of quotas, they correspond either to
    period or to quantity or number of items. Quotas may be set according to
    various types.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Period</title>

      <para>Quotas linked to period work all in the same way : a default value
      (14 see below) is used if no particular specified value is
      applicable.</para>

      <para>This value is set in <emphasis>General parameters</emphasis> in
      the <emphasis>default value <emphasis><emphasis>fields</emphasis>
      by</emphasis> XXX if left unspecified</emphasis>. It is a period given
      in days. If <emphasis>calendar</emphasis> is not enabled in
      <emphasis>General parameters</emphasis> and the opening days of the
      library are not set accordingly PMB sees all seven days of the week
      equally. Thus Monday will be counted as one day just like Sunday.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Quotas : default value for a duration quota in PMB</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/quota-defaut-duree.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Quantity</title>

      <para>Quotas linked to quantity work all in the same way : a default
      value is used if no particular specified value is applicable.</para>

      <para>This value is defined in <emphasis>General parameters</emphasis>
      in the <emphasis>default value<emphasis>
      </emphasis><emphasis><emphasis>fields</emphasis> by</emphasis> XXX if
      left unspecified</emphasis>. This value points to the number of works,
      serials or holds corresponding to only ONE type of document. Quotas
      linked to quantity also have a field to enter the maximum quota allowed.
      This maximum represents the absolute quota across works, serials or
      holds collectively. If the default value is set at 5 and no other value
      is entered, the reader will have the right to hold, borrow 5 CDs and 5
      books all at the same time. If the maximum is set at 7, he will be able
      to have 7 works only, of which a maximum of 5 CDs or 5 books.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Quotas : default values for quantity linked quotas in
        PMB</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/quota_defauts.gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Types of quotas</title>

      <para>There are five types of quotas linked to quantity or
      period:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>by Readers categories</para>

          <para>A quota may be set for each borrower category in the column
          "Number of items". To delete a quota, clear the value entered in the
          check box. Warning, 0 does not mean no quota at all, but one whose
          value is set to 0, that is, loan not allowed.</para>

          <para>You may authorize (or not) override quota for each of the
          readers categories. If a quota is reached by one reader in a
          particular category, the librarian may then authorize a loan issue,
          that is, override the stop loan directive.</para>

          <para><figure>
              <title>Quotas by readers categories</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/quota_categ_lect.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>by Media types</para>

          <para>A quota may be set for each type of document. It works exactly
          like quotas by readers categories <figure>
              <title>Quotas by media types</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/quota_type_exp.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>by Readers categories and by Media types</para>

          <para>Here you may cross Readers categories with Media types to
          refine your loans policy. Quotas are displayed in the form of a
          table sub-listing all the media types under each Readers
          category.<figure>
              <title>Quotas by Readers categories and by Media types</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/quota_categ_lect_et_type.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>by Individual readers</para>

          <para>Functions exactly like by Readers categories, but individually
          for every reader of your library.<figure>
              <title>Quotas by individual readers</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/quota_lecteurs.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>by Media types and by Individual readers</para>

          <para>Functions exactly like by Readers categories and by Media
          types, but individually for every reader of your library.<figure>
              <title>Quotas by individual Readers and by Media types</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/quota_lecteurs_types.gif" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Example.</emphasis> By defining a quota
      linked to Number of items by Readers categories and by Media types, you
      could thus grant students the right to borrow 2 CD audio.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>The various quotas</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>number of items</title>

      <para>We are talking here about defining the number of items that can be
      borrowed simultaneously.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>loan period</title>

      <para>This comes under loans management (advanced) relating to loan
      period of copies of works.</para>

      <para>There are five types of quotas by loan period : by Readers
      categories, by Media types, by Readers categories and by Media types, by
      Individual readers, and finally by Media types and by Individual
      readers.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>number of holds</title>

      <para>This refers to loans management relating to the number of items
      (except serials) that can be placed on hold simultaneously.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>hold duration</title>

      <para>This comes under loans management (advanced) relating to duration
      of hold for works (except serials).</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>number of serials holds</title>

      <para>This refers to loans management relating to the number of items
      (serials only) that can be placed on hold simultaneously.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>serials hold duration</title>

      <para>This comes under loans management (advanced) relating to duration
      of hold for serials.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>In case of conflict</title>

    <para>In addition to the default values (see further up Quotas : period,
    quantity and types), the general parameters allow you to choose how to
    resolve conflicts between quotas. Since you can define quotas by
    individual readers and by categories as well, you will have to decide
    which one has precedence over the other.</para>

    <para>In case of conflict between several quotas, you can choose among
    <emphasis>Take the largest</emphasis> (full authorization policy)
    <emphasis>Take the smallest</emphasis>(full restriction policy),
    <emphasis>Take the default value </emphasis>(if both values clash, it's
    the default value that be used to resolve the conflict), enfin de
    <emphasis>Process according to a specified directive</emphasis> the
    various quotas.</para>

    <para>If you choose to retain this option, you can use list-down menus to
    indicate the order of precedence of your types of quotas.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Quotas : in case of conflict</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/quota_conflits.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>You may also leave it to your staff at the issue counter to decide
    in principle whether to <emphasis>authorize a loan thus overriding the
    quota directive</emphasis>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Defining a quota</title>

    <para>Let's take an example. In our library, children are allowed three
    items of which a maximum of two books, two items from the Deparmental
    Lending Library, one CD audio, one video recording. For a school project
    the children may on request be allowed more than two items from the
    Deparmental Lending Library (forcing the loan directive for this type of
    document and the total number of items allowed at the same time).</para>

    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para>On the <emphasis>Administration</emphasis> tab, click on
        <emphasis>Quotas</emphasis> in the side menu</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>Next click on <emphasis>Number of items</emphasis> quota</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>Click on quota type by Readers categories</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>For the category <emphasis><emphasis
        role="bold">Children</emphasis></emphasis>, enter <emphasis
        role="bold">2</emphasis> for number of items, and <emphasis
        role="bold">clear</emphasis> <emphasis>Override
        quota</emphasis></para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>Click on Save</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>Click on quota type <emphasis>by Readers categories and by Media
        types</emphasis>.</para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>For the category <emphasis><emphasis
        role="bold">Children</emphasis></emphasis>, enter <emphasis
        role="bold">2</emphasis> for number of items
        <emphasis>Book</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="bold">clear</emphasis>
        <emphasis>Override quota</emphasis></para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>Again for the category <emphasis><emphasis
        role="bold">Children</emphasis></emphasis>, enter <emphasis
        role="bold">2</emphasis> for number of items <emphasis>BDP
        items</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="bold">tick</emphasis>
        <emphasis>No override</emphasis></para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>Once again for the category <emphasis><emphasis
        role="bold">Children</emphasis></emphasis>, enter <emphasis
        role="bold">1</emphasis> for number of items <emphasis>CD
        Audio</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis> for number of
        items <emphasis>Video recording</emphasis>, and <emphasis
        role="bold">tick</emphasis> <emphasis>No override</emphasis></para>
      </step>

      <step>
        <para>Click on Save</para>

        <para>Your quotas are now defined. Vous may eventually customize the
        general parameter to suit your needs.</para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </sect1>
</chapter>