<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="admin_notices">
  <title lang="en">Records</title>

  <para lang="en">Most of the data defining a record are standardized. However
  PMB allows the editing of a table originating from a bibliographical record.
  You can also add customizable fields.</para>

  <sect1 id="admin_notices_orinot">
    <title lang="en">Sources</title>

    <para lang="en">This represents the source of a bibliographical record.
    PMB imports records mainly via z39.50 or through UNIMARC import. However
    these records are copyrighted. Records from the Bibliothèque Nationale de
    France [National Library, France] can be used freely, however this might
    not necessarily be the case for some professionals in this domain. Indeed,
    the company Electre publishes a CD-Rom of bibliographical records, updated
    with the latest publications. This CD-Rom is not free, and each one of its
    bibliographical records are copyrighted.</para>

    <para lang="en">Since version 1.3, PMB keeps track of sources of
    bibliographical records.</para>

    <para lang="en">The administrative function for sources of records allows
    to pre-define these sources. It also allows the editing of sources of
    imported records.</para>

    <figure>
      <title lang="en">Records &gt; sources</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_cat_notices.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title lang="en">Status</title>

    <para lang="en">The status of records allows to set distinct properties to
    records at processing and cataloguing levels, and whether they are to be
    displayed in OPAC as well.</para>

    <figure>
      <title lang="en">Records &gt; Status</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_notices_statut.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">The records status table shows various information:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">a display class (1 to 9), corresponds to a color
        rectangle on the left of the table. This marker quickly identifies the
        status of the record, for example, when using the cataloguing tab for
        a search.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">whether visible or not from the PMB management tab.
        This will allow the management of a "reservoir of records", for
        example, by saving destroyed records with a "destroy" status.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para lang="en">for the OPAC,</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">potential label (e.g. on order)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">visibility of records</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">displaying copies</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para lang="en">displaying e-copies (electronic copies)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para lang="en">To add a new status to a record, click on the appropriate
    button at the bottom of the screen.</para>

    <para lang="en">To edit the status of a record, click on the corresponding
    line in the table,</para>

    <figure>
      <title lang="en">Records &gt; Status, modify status</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_notices_statut2.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">From the edit screen, you can also restrict the display of
    records, copies, e-copies to subscribers only (readers and borrowers with
    a login and password). If restrictions apply, the reader will have to be
    identified in order to remove these restrictions.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="admin_notices_perso">
    <title lang="en">Customizable data</title>

    <para lang="en">Here we are talking of customizable fields of records.
    These customizable fields allow you to specify any information about your
    own library or documentation center within the records: origin of idea to
    acquire the work, commentary of a reading committee, intended
    audience...</para>

    <figure>
      <title lang="en">Records &gt; Customizable data</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_cat_perso_notice.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">Customizable fields for records work the same way as those
    for copies. For more information, refer to <xref
    linkend="admin_expl_perso" />.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>