<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="admin_users">
  <title lang="en">Users</title>

  <para lang="en">In PMB, the <emphasis>user</emphasis> denomination refers to the
  application users and not the library users, that is readers or borrowers. A
  user is for example : a library assistant at the issue counter, a librarian,
  a network administrator, ...</para>

  <sect1>
    <title lang="en">Managing users</title>

    <para lang="en">The PMB users managment section will allow you to create users'
    profiles. For each user account, a username and a password is created. PMB
    needs at least an administrator account (Super User). This account cannot
    be removed from within PMB.</para>

    <para lang="en">If you have loaded the PMB test data set, you also have three
    additional accounts : librarian (user : <emphasis>bib</emphasis>, password
    : <emphasis>bib</emphasis>), cataloguer (<emphasis>cat</emphasis> ;
    <emphasis>cat</emphasis>) and library assistant
    (<emphasis>circ</emphasis>: <emphasis>circ</emphasis>)</para>

    <para lang="en">Access privileges to the various parts of the software are managed
    by enabling the tabs. Depending on whether access is granted (open
    padlock) or not (closed padlock), the corresponding tab will be displayed
    or not on the management interface. With one exception to the rule : the
    backup feature is not displayed as a tab.</para>

    <para lang="en">Here you can edit a user's account and change his password. This last
    feature is useful when a user takes up another job or when a password
    is lost. The user may change his password on his own without having to ask the
    network administrator to do it, by clicking on user preferences (preferences
    link on the top right of the screen).</para>

    <figure>
      <title lang="en">Managing users</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_util_gestion.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para lang="en">A user's account, accessible by clicking on the edit button, refer to users' preferences accessible from the <emphasis>edit user's parameters</emphasis> link next to the <emphasis>logout</emphasis> link.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>