<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="admin_calendrier">
  <title>Calendar</title>

  <para>You can choose to use the integrated calendar within PMB to manage the
  library's opening days. If the calendar is enabled, the whole arithmetic
  linked with loans (overdues, loan period, ...) will be based on the calendar
  of opening days of the library and not on the 7-day week.</para>

  <para>Important : The calendar will be used for return dates or holds
  available. The first day of opening following or falling on the expected
  date will be the one retained.</para>

  <sect1>
    <title>If the Calendar is not enabled</title>

    <para><graphic fileref="images/warning.gif" /></para>

    <para>if the calendar is not enabled, you will not see "calendar" in the
    menu.</para>

    <para>For more details on activating the calendar of opening days, see
    <xref linkend="admin_expl_typdoc" />.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Defining opening days</title>

    <figure>
      <title>Figure 8.1. Administration &gt; Calendar &gt;
      Consultation</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/quota-defaut-duree.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Once parameter use_calendar in general parameters has been set to 1,
    click on the Administration tab to make Calendar appear in the side
    menu.</para>

    <para>In the form, enter the period you wish to modify, for example,
    01/09/2006 - 31/08/2006.</para>

    <para>Tick the days affected by your action : for example, monday,
    wednesday, thursday. Click on open to declare these days as the opening
    days of the library.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Figure 8.2. Administration &gt; Calendar &gt;
      Consultation</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/quota-defaut-duree.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>To close for Christmas : enter the period you wish to modify :
    20/12/2006 - 05/01/2007. Tick the days affected by your action monday,
    wednesday, thursday then click on Close.</para>

    <para>To modify a day manually, simply click on the number of the day, it
    will turn from green to "not green" and vice-versa.</para>

    <para>To move from one year to another, use the green arrows under the
    form.</para>

    <para>Reminder : The calendar will be used to calculate return dates or
    holds available. The first day of opening following or falling on the
    expected date will be the one retained.</para>

    <para>Example : the return date of an item falls during Christmas
    holidays, the return date is therefore automatically reset at 06/01/2007
    (or failing opening on that day on the next opening day).</para>

    <para>Note : you have to write a note linked with your action : "Great,
    it's Christmas" or "Closed exceptionally". To edit a note for a particular
    day, click on the month, a form showing all the days of the month is
    displayed along with the corresponding notes.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>