<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="definitions">
  <title>A few definitions</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Readers and borrowers</title>

    <para>In PMB and in this guide, the word borrowers carries the same meaning as the word reader. These two are used interchangeably.</para></sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Barcode or keyboard input</title>

    <para>PMB was conceived to be used with a bar code reader. The bar code reader does not require any special setting. It is connected to the computer's USB port or connects between the computer and the keyboard (PS/2 port).</para>

    <para>  </para>

    <para>We recommend the use of a barcode reader (approximately € 150 for a USB model).</para>

    <para>You can also enter the barcode with the keyboard and press Enter instead of using the barcode reader.</para></sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Works and copies</title>

    <para>A book is described in a bibliographical note. A Library can possess many copies of a book, some copies can be excluded from loan, while others can be borrowed.</para>

    <para>The book bibliographical note represents a description of a work that the library might own or not. Copies of this work can be precisely identified in a library.</para>

    <para>For a book, both a bibliographical note and a copy will be present in PMB. For two copies of a same book, both a bibliographical note and 2 copies will therefore be present in PMB.</para></sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>UNIMARC bibliographic format</title>

    <para>UNIMARC is a standard for bibliographic data exchange.</para>

    <para>A UNIMARC note is composed of various numbered blocs corresponding to various types of information. Each bloc is composed for fields and sub-fields. Fields are numbered, subfields are preceded by the $ sign followed by a letter.</para>

    <para>Here is an example of a UNIMARC file for a copy with barcode 5777008954 of:</para>

    <address>Les Champignons / Jean C. Keller. - Paris: le Livre de poche, 1983 - 127 p.: ill. ; 17 cm. - (Le Livre de poche&nbsp;; 7847).</address>

    <programlisting>*****cam**22002411**450*                       [Coded data] 010 ** $a 2-253-03268-9 $b Br. $d 24 F         [ISBN, binding, price] 100 ** $a 19840104d1983****m**y0frey0103****ba [Coded data] 101 ** $a fre                                  [Language code and numbers] 102 ** $a FR                                   [Country identification code] 105 ** $a aay**zz**00|z|                       [Coded data] 106 ** $a r                                    [Coded Data] 200 1* $a Les Champignons $f Jean C. Keller    [Title and publisher] 210 *0 $a Paris $c le Livre de poche $d 1983   [Bibliographical address] 215 ** $a 127 p. $c ill. $d 17 cm              [Collation] 225 2* $a Le Livre de poche $v 7847            [Collection] 606 ** $3 $a Champignons                       [Subject Catchword] 676 ** $a 589.2                                [Dewey Index] 700 1* $a Keller $b Jean                       [Principal Author catchword] 995 ** $f 5777008954 $k 589.2 KEL
</ulink>
(1) the * represent blanks or non filled positions (2) the words between brackets [] are not part of a UNIMARC file and are mentioned here to help in reading</programlisting>

    <para>For more information on the UNIMARC format, refer to this excellent link <ulink url="http://www.cg95.fr/biblio/bdvo/coinbib/iso2709/">http://www.cg95.fr/biblio/bdvo/coinbib/iso2709/</ulink> or perform a Google search on UNIMARC.</para>

    <para>PMB can import and export data with a UNIMARC format.</para></sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>BDP, recommendation 995</title>

    <para>BDP (Biblioth&egrave;que D&eacute;partementale de Pr&ecirc;t) stands for Loan Departmental Library. In France, these libraries generally have a role as lender to other libraries within their network. These deposited books are then loaned by libraries to their readers.</para>

    <para>The recommendation 995 was published by ABF, ADBDP and FULBI with the help of the culture ministry (Direction du livre et de la lecture, Book and Reading Directorate). Its purpose is to simplify bibliographical data exchange related to book copies within the 995 UNIMARC zone. PMB supports the recommendation 995 et allows imports of UNIMARC files, for example for a BDP deposit in one of the libraries of its network.</para></sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>UNIMARC Copy Import and Import Coding</title>

    <para>Information in the 995 UNIMARC zone relate to copies. However this information does not correspond to precise lists of document types, statistical codes, etc... To allow importing this information, a relational relationship with existing tables is attempted. The codes encountered in a UNIMARC file are then considered by PMB as import codes.</para>

    <para>While importing, these codes are added to the preexisting codes in PMB, for example to the list of document types (visible in Administration &gt; Copies &gt; Document types).</para>

    <para>After any import, le data contained in Administration &gt; Copies must then be cleaned-up to allow cross-checking, because systematically adding import codes can pollute the database.</para>

    <para>In the various information lists for copies, you will find a column of import codes and an import owner column. These columns enable linking with the imported information.</para></sect1></chapter>
