<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="definitions">
  <title>A few definitions</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Readers and borrowers</title>

    <para>In PMB and in this guide, the word borrower carries the same meaning
    as the word reader. Both are used interchangeably.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Barcode scan or keyboard input</title>

    <para>PMB was conceived to be used with a barcode scanner. Barcode
    scanners do not require any special setting. It is connected to the
    computer's USB port or placed between the computer and the keyboard (PS/2
    port).</para>

    <para>Scanning means reading a barcode with a scanner in PMB
    Administrator's Guide.</para>

    <para>We recommend the use of a scanner (approximately 150 Euros for a USB
    model).</para>

    <para>You can also enter the barcode with the keyboard and press Enter
    instead of using the scanner.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Records and copies</title>

    <para>A book is described in a bibliographical record, or simply record. A
    library can possess many copies of a book, some copies can be excluded
    from loan, while others can be borrowed.</para>

    <para>The record represents a description of a work owned or not by the
    library. Copies or items allow to distinguish precisely between each of
    the copies of one and same book in a library.</para>

    <para>For a book, both a record and a copy will be present in PMB. For two
    copies of one and same book, there will be 1 record and 2 copies in
    PMB.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>UNIMARC bibliographic format</title>

    <para>UNIMARC is a standard for bibliographic data exchange.</para>

    <para>A UNIMARC record is composed of various numbered blocks
    corresponding to various types of data. Each block is made up of fields
    and sub-fields. Fields are numbered, while sub-fields are preceded by the
    $ sign followed by a letter.</para>

    <para>Here is an example of a UNIMARC file for a copy with barcode
    5777008954 of:</para>

    <address>Les Champignons / Jean C. Keller. - Paris: le Livre de poche, 1983 - 127 p.: ill. ; 17 cm. - (Le Livre de poche&nbsp;; 7847).</address>

    <programlisting>*****cam**22002411**450*                       [Coded data]
010 ** $a 2-253-03268-9 $b Br. $d 24 F         [ISBN, binding, price] 
100 ** $a 19840104d1983****m**y0frey0103****ba [Coded data] 
101 ** $a fre                                  [Language code and numbers] 
102 ** $a FR                                   [Country identification code] 
105 ** $a aay**zz**00|z|                       [Coded data] 
106 ** $a r                                    [Coded Data] 
200 1* $a Les Champignons $f Jean C. Keller    [Title and publisher] 
210 *0 $a Paris $c le Livre de poche $d 1983   [Bibliographical address] 
215 ** $a 127 p. $c ill. $d 17 cm              [Collation] 
225 2* $a Le Livre de poche $v 7847            [Collection] 
606 ** $3 $a Champignons                       [Subject Catchword] 
676 ** $a 589.2                                [Dewey Index] 
700 1* $a Keller $b Jean                       [Principal Author catchword] 
995 ** $f 5777008954 $k 589.2 KEL

(1) the * represent blanks or non filled positions 
(2) the words in brackets [] are not part of a UNIMARC file and are mentioned here to help understand</programlisting>

    <para>For more information on the UNIMARC format, refer to this excellent
    link <ulink
    url="http://www.cg95.fr/biblio/bdvo/coinbib/iso2709/">http://www.cg95.fr/biblio/bdvo/coinbib/iso2709/</ulink>
    or perform a Google search on UNIMARC.</para>

    <para>PMB can import and export data with a UNIMARC format.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>BDP, recommendation 995</title>

    <para>BDP stands for Bibliothèque Départementale de Prêt [Departmental
    Lending Library]. In France, these libraries generally function as lending
    libraries managing interlibrary loans for other libraries within their
    network. Books deposited are then loaned by these libraries to their
    readers.</para>

    <para>Recommendation 995 was published by ABF, ADBDP and FULBI with the
    full support of the Ministry of Culture [Book and Reading Directorate],
    (France). Its purpose is to simplify bibliographical data exchange related
    to book copies in zone 995 UNIMARC. PMB supports recommendation 995 and
    allows imports of UNIMARC files, for example, for a BDP depot in one of
    the libraries within its network.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>UNIMARC Copy Import and Import Coding</title>

    <para>Data in the zone 995 UNIMARC relate to copies. But these data do not
    correspond to precise lists of document types, statistical codes, etc...
    To allow these data to be imported, an attempt is made to create a
    relationship with existing tables. The codes from the UNIMARC file are
    then processed by PMB as import codes.</para>

    <para>During the import process, these codes are added to the pre-existing
    codes in PMB, for example, to the list of document types (visible in
    Administration &gt; Copies &gt; Document types).</para>

    <para>After an import, it is necessary to cleanup the data contained in
    Administration &gt; Copies to allow cross-checking, as adding import codes
    systematically can pollute the database.</para>

    <para>You will find a column for import codes and another one for the
    import owner in the various information lists for copies. These columns
    enable you to find the link with imported data.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>