<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="admin_notices">
  <title>Records</title>

  <para>Most of the data defining a record are standardized. However PMB
  allows the editing of a table originating from a bibliographical record. You
  can also add customizable fields.</para>

  <sect1 id="admin_notices_orinot">
    <title>Sources</title>

    <para>This represents the source of a bibliographical record. PMB imports
    records mainly via z39.50 or through UNIMARC import. However these records
    are copyrighted. Records from the Bibliothèque Nationale de France
    [National Library, France] can be used freely, however this might not
    necessarily be the case for some professionals in this domain. Indeed, the
    company Electre publishes a CD-Rom of bibliographical records, updated
    with the latest publications. This CD-Rom is not free, and each one of its
    bibliographical records are copyrighted.</para>

    <para>Since version 1.3, PMB keeps track of source of bibliographical
    records.</para>

    <para>The administrative function for sources of records allows to
    pre-define these sources. It also allows the editing of sources of
    imported records.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Notes &gt; Notes sources</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_cat_notices.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Status</title>

    <para>The status of records allows to set distinct properties to records
    at processing and cataloguing levels, and whether they are to be displayed
    in OPAC as well.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Notes &gt; Status</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_notices_statut.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The records status table shows various information:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>a display class (1 to 9), corresponds to a color rectangle on
        the left of the table. This marker quickly identifies the status of
        the record, for example, when using the cataloguing tab for a
        search.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>whether visible or not from the PMB management tab. This will
        allow the management of a "reservoir of records", for example, by
        saving destroyed records with a "destroy" status.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>for the OPAC,</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>potential label (e.g. on order)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>visibility of records</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>display of copies</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>display of e-copies (electronic copies)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>To add a new status to a record, click on the appropriate button at
    the bottom of the screen.</para>

    <para>To edit the status of a record, click on the corresponding line in
    the table,</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Notes &gt; Status, modify the status</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_notices_statut2.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>From the edit screen, you can also restrict the display of records,
    copies, e-copies to subscribers only (readers and borrowers with a login
    and password). If restrictions apply, the reader will have to be
    identified in order to remove these restrictions.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="admin_notices_perso">
    <title>Customizable data</title>

    <para>Here we are talking of customizable fields of records. These
    customizable fields allow you to specify any information about your own
    library or documentation center within the records: origin of idea to
    acquire the work, commentary of a reading committee, intended
    audience...</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Notes &gt; Customizable data</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/admin_cat_perso_notice.gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Customizable fields for records work the same way as those for
    copies. For more information, refer to <xref
    linkend="admin_expl_perso" />.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>